<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blu-bird.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://blu-bird.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-30T22:56:43+00:00</updated><id>https://blu-bird.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">topological revisionism</title><link href="https://blu-bird.github.io/blog/2024/revision/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="topological revisionism"/><published>2024-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blu-bird.github.io/blog/2024/revision</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blu-bird.github.io/blog/2024/revision/"><![CDATA[<p>this past quarter i started my journey of learning ✨algebraic geometry✨! yippee</p> <p>As of right now I’m planning on taking a year-long sequence following Hartshorne<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> primarily, supplemented by Liu’s <em>Algebraic Geometry and Arithmetic Curves</em> and Vakil’s <em>The Rising Sea</em>. This quarter we started from thinking about varieties cut out of \(k^n\) (for \(k\) characteristic zero, algebraically closed) and eventually made the Big Leap of Abstraction to schemes. I know some people like teaching algebraic geometry by jumping straight into thinking about sheaves and schemes, but I really liked working through the embedded varieties content in Chapter I of Hartshorne. Having worked with concrete examples before looking at Chapter II was super helpful for my visual intuition for schemes. Also, having nice results to replicate from Chapter I made me more invested in the lemmas we were proving when we got to more abstract stuff. Had I jumped straight into schemes first, I think I would have really struggled with both of these things, so I really appreciated our class’ emphasis on the classical viewpoint. Making the leap to schemes is really difficult because of all of the abstract machinery needed, and having seen reflections of some of the geometrical ideas with an embedded variety beforehand was nice.</p> <p>I started learning algebraic geometry having done a good amount of differential topology but with a pretty weak commutative algebra background<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, so see below for my live reaction to learning that schemes are spaces that are “locally isomorphic to \(\spec\) of a ring”:</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <div style="width: 300px; margin: 0 auto; color: #fff;"> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/revision/ag-meme-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/revision/ag-meme-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/posts/revision/ag-meme-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/revision/ag-meme.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> just slap a chart on it! </div> </div> </div> <p>This mindset tends to do really well when dealing with manifolds! Working with charts and coordinates in \(\RR^n\) is nice since one can write down functions explicitly, or use matrices and linear algebra when talking about differentials and tangent spaces. So when you have one trick and every scheme looks like a manifold waiting to be hit by it, I really don’t think it’s necessarily a bad idea!</p> <p>Unfortunately, I felt like I got burned by this because now instead of doing calculus and linear algebra, the right tool to use is now commutative algebra… which I’m currently bad at. And instead of being able to do all the analysis shenanigans I want in \(\RR^n\), now we’re dealing with prime ideals of a general ring and the Zariski topology, and working with \(\spec R\) directly is not as good of a time. I had to learn the hard way that thinking about the sheaf of sections and its stalks are more lucrative for schemes because of their nice descriptions in terms of localizations in the affine case. In his lead-up to talking about schemes in Chapter 3 of <em>The Rising Sea</em>, Vakil hints that this is a more useful way to think about a geometric space in general:</p> <blockquote> <p>… The key insight behind this generalization from the notion of something like a manifold to a more versatile notion of a “geometric space” is the following: we can understand a geometric space (such as a manifold) well by understanding the functions on this space. More precisely, we will understand it through the sheaf of functions on the space.</p> </blockquote> <p>To be honest, though, I found this a bit counterintuitive because while I’ve worked with \(C^\infty(M)\) on a manifold before as well as germs at a point \(C^\infty_{M, p}\) for a point \(p \in M\), these rings don’t seem relatively nice<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. There are tons of zero-divisors (just think about functions making up of a partition of unity, for instance) and it doesn’t seem clear to me that this ring of functions has enough structure in it to tell you much directly about the about topological structure of the manifold.</p> <p>But then I saw the following <a href="https://x.com/barbarafantechi/status/1868370463044555048?s=46">tweet</a> from algebraic geometer Barbara Fantechi:</p> <blockquote> <p>… I have told my students for decades that 1) one can work with embedded or abstract manifolds and varieties/schemes 2) they all can be described as space plus (equivalence chart of) atlas, or as locally ringed space, or by their functor of points. … Getting rid of such cultural barriers would make communication between algebraic and differential geometry MUCH easier!</p> </blockquote> <p>Generally, it feels like the communication tends to go from differential geometry to algebraic geometry, which I think is really helpful in the learning process. A lot of algebraic geometry adjectives are described in analogy to certain concepts from manifolds, and having nice topological intuition when working with the Zariski topology is a good thing. But let’s try to go the other way now and see what it would take to impose the language of algebraic geometry onto differential geometry! This at first glance seems to be doable, since manifolds are a much more specialized kind of object in comparison to locally ringed spaces and schemes. But is there really a way to think about a manifold as a locally ringed space instead of as a space with an atlas?</p> <h3 id="hey-wait-dont-yell-at-me">hey wait don’t yell at me</h3> <p>Before we start, if you’re really looking to nitpick definitions in differential geometry or if you need a refresher on what manifold things mean, go ahead and expand this so you know what I’m talking about when I say various words:</p> <details><summary>the definitions that i’m choosing to use thanks</summary> <p>Let’s recall what a standard definition of a (smooth) manifold looks like:</p> <blockquote> <p>Definition. A <em>smooth manifold</em> is a pair \((M, \mc A)\) where \(M\) is a <em>second-countable Hausdorff</em> topological space, and \(\mc A\) is a <em>maximal atlas</em> of <em>charts</em>. A chart is a map \(\vphi_i\) from \(U_i \subseteq M\) open to \(\RR^n\) that restricts to a homeomorphism on its image, and an atlas is a collection of charts that are <em>compatible</em>, so that the <em>transition maps</em> \(\vphi_j \circ \vphi_i^{-1} : \vphi_i(U_i \cap U_j) \to \vphi_j(U_i \cap U_j)\) is smooth as functions on Euclidean spaces.</p> </blockquote> <p>I will very often drop “smooth” as an adjective for manifold. We also might as well define smooth maps between them too, just to fill out the morphisms in our category:</p> <blockquote> <p>Definition. A <em>smooth map</em> between two manifolds \(M\) and \(N\) is a continuous map \(f : M \to N\) such that for every pair of charts \(\vphi : U \to \RR^m\) of \(M\) and \(\psi : V \to \RR^n\) of \(N\) with \(f(U) \subseteq V\), the map \(\psi \circ f \circ \vphi^{-1} : \vphi(U) \to \psi(V)\) is smooth.</p> </blockquote> <p>Note that in both definitions, we have to deal with weird domain restriction business so the relevant charts overlap in the right places. We also see that “smoothness” of both of these definitions also essentially comes inherited from the smoothness of maps between Euclidean spaces, so we should expect any new definitions to do the same.</p> <p>Some sources don’t require manifolds to be second-countable and Hausdorff, but I do because I want my partitions of unity. (Apologies to long line and double-origin enthusiasts.) Just as a reminder:</p> <blockquote> <p>Definition. A <em>partition of unity</em> subordinate to an open cover \(\set{U_i}_{i \in I}\) of \(M\) is a collection of smooth real-valued functions \(\set{\rho_i}_{i \in I}\) such that (1) \(\rho_i \geq 0\), with \(\supp \rho_i \subseteq U_i\), (2) \(\set{\supp \rho_i}_{i \in I}\) is locally finite, i.e. any point is only contained in finitely many of these sets, and (3) \(\sum_{i \in I} \rho_i = 1_M\).</p> </blockquote> <p>With the second-countable/Hausdorff requirement for a manifold, <em>any</em> open cover of \(M\) has a partition of unity suboordinate to it. In particular, in the construction of this partition of unity, one can make \(I\) countable and the supports \(\supp \rho_i\) all compact. This feels like it’s a little restrictive, but this is actually ok since manifolds are now paracompact and \(\sigma\)-compact (open covers have locally finite refinements/is union of countably many compact subsets). This will be useful later.</p> <p>As a final remark, one can generalize everything to be a \(C^\alpha\)-manifold where the transition maps and morphisms are \(C^\alpha\) functions on Euclidean spaces instead of smooth ones, but today we generally don’t care about any values of \(\alpha\) other than \(\alpha = \infty\) and maybe \(\alpha = 0\). It would be interesting to think about how the below arguments change if you allow less smooth/more smooth (i.e. real analytic/\(C^\omega\)) functions instead.</p> </details> <p>…</p> <p>are we all on the same page about what a manifold is? okay great let’s get to translating!</p> <h3 id="first-cracks-in-the-cultural-wall">first cracks in the cultural wall</h3> <p>this translation idea is not an uncommon one, and more or less appears in Vakil’s <em>The Rising Sea</em> as Definition 4.3.9. We present here instead a slightly more stringent series of definitions and arguments coming from Torsten Wedhorn’s <em>Manifolds, Sheaves, and Cohomology</em>, Sections 4.1-4.2.</p> <blockquote> <p>Definition. A smooth manifold is a pair \((M, \cOO_M)\) where \(M\) is a second-countable Hausdorff topological space and \(\cOO_M\) is a sheaf of local \(\RR\)-algebras, such that any point of \(M\) has an open neighborhood \(U\) with \((U, \cOO_M\vert_U)\) isomorphic to \((X, C^\infty_X)\) as a locally ringed space, where \(X \subseteq \RR^n\) is an open set and \(C^\infty_X\) is the sheaf of real-valued smooth functions on \(X\).</p> </blockquote> <p>Vakil only requires that we have rings, but I think it’s not too hard to convince ourselves that we probably should elevate our ringed space to be one with a sheaf of \(\RR\)-algebras, since \(C^\infty(X)\) for \(X \subseteq \RR^n\) open is an \(\RR\)-algebra. As such, Wedhorn calls \(M\) a <em>locally \(\RR\)-ringed space</em>, since our sheaf is valued in the category of \(\RR\)-algebras instead of just rings, which I think is a sensible naming convention.</p> <p>Note that this definition doesn’t actually <em>tell</em> us what the sheaf of \(\RR\)-algebras on \(M\) is, just that it’s locally isomorphic to the sheaf of real-valued smooth functions on \(\RR^n\). However, we’d like to say <em>in general</em> that our sheaf on \(M\) is just the sheaf of smooth real-valued functions on \(M\), as we might expect (Proposition 4.17). To help us, let’s also look at what smooth maps of manifolds should be now:</p> <blockquote> <p>Definition. A morphism (smooth map) of manifolds \(f : M \to N\) is a morphism as locally ringed spaces.</p> </blockquote> <p>To characterize our given sheaf \(\cOO_M\), let’s define the sheaf \(C^\infty_M\), where \(C^\infty_M(U)\) is the set of morphisms (smooth maps) \(h : U \to \RR\) for \(U \subseteq M\) open, and \(\RR\) having its sheaf of real-valued smooth functions \(C^\infty_\RR\). The underlying continuous maps \(U \to \RR\) have the structure of an \(\RR\)-algebra via pointwise addition/multiplication/scaling. The corresponding maps on sheaves \(h^\sharp (Y): C^\infty_\RR (Y) \to \cOO_M\vert_U(h^{-1}(Y))\) for any \(Y \subseteq \RR\) open have the structure of an \(\RR\)-algebra as well, since \(\cOO_M\vert_U\) is a \(\RR\)-algebra-valued sheaf on \(U\) and so one can naturally define for any morphisms \(h_1, h_2\) and a real \(c \in \RR\) the sheaf maps \((h_1 + h_2)^\sharp\), \((h_1 h_2)^\sharp\), and \((c h_1)^\sharp\) in terms of \(h_1^\sharp\) and \(h_2^\sharp\). Therefore, \(C^\infty_M\) is a sheaf of \(\RR\)-algebras on \(M\) as well.</p> <p>Now we construct a morphism of sheaves \(\iota : C^\infty_M \to \cOO_M\) in the following way. Take a morphism \(h : U \to \RR\) in \(C^\infty_M(U)\) and consider the map on sheaves \(h^\sharp : C^\infty_\RR \to h_* (\cOO_M\vert_U)\). Then in \(C^\infty_\RR(\RR)\), we have the smooth function \(\id_\RR\), which under \(h^\sharp(\RR)\) gives an element \(h^\sharp(\RR)(\id_\RR) \in \cOO_M\vert_U(U) = \cOO_M(U)\). Then \(\iota(U)\) should be defined to send \(h \mapsto h^\sharp(\RR)(\id_\RR)\) for any \(U \subseteq M\) open. A direct computation shows</p> <details><summary>this is indeed a morphism :)</summary> <p>Take any \(V \subseteq U\) open. It suffices to verify that \(\iota(V) \circ \rho^U_{C^\infty_M, V} = \rho^U_{\cOO_M, V} \circ \iota(U)\), where the \(\rho^U_{\mc F, V}\)s are the appropriate restriction maps on each sheaf \(\mc F\) from \(U\) to \(V\). Taking an arbitrary \(h \in C^\infty_M(U)\), the left-hand side evaluates to \(\iota(V) (h \circ i) = (h \circ i)^\sharp(\RR)(\id_\RR)\), where \(i : V \to U\) is the natural inclusion. This decomposes further as \(i^\sharp(h^{-1}(\RR)) \circ h^\sharp(\RR)(\id_\RR)\), but this is now precisely the right-hand side, as the sheaf map \(i^\sharp\) is exactly the restriction map on the sheaf \(\cOO_M\), as desired.</p> </details> <p>…</p> <p>Now, to show this is an isomorphism, we can check this locally. In particular, it suffices to check this on some \(U \subseteq M\) isomorphic to an open set \(X \subseteq \RR^n\). But then if we take some \(g : X \to \RR\) a morphism, then \(g^\sharp(\RR)(\id_\RR) = \id_\RR \circ g = g\), so this is obviously an isomorphism. This means that the sheaf we defined on \(M\) in general is always secretly just its sheaf of smooth functions!</p> <p>Here, we used the fact that if we have \(X \subseteq \RR^n\) and \(Y \subseteq \RR^m\) open, for any morphism \(f : X \to Y\) viewed as locally ringed spaces with sheaves of smooth functions, the sheaf map \(f^\sharp\) must be given by precomposing by \(f\) (Example 4.5). Consider the following commutative diagram for any \(V \subseteq Y\) open:</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <div style="width: 180px; margin: 0 auto; color: #fff;"> <script type="text/tikz">
  \tikzcdset{color=white}
  \begin{tikzcd}
    C^\infty_Y(V) \arrow[r, "f^\sharp(V)", white] 
    \arrow[d, "l_{f(x)}", white]
      & C^\infty_X(f^{-1}(V)) \arrow[d, "l_x", white] \\
    C^\infty_{Y, f(x)} \arrow[r, "f^\sharp_x", white]
    \arrow[d, "\pi_{f(x)}", white] &  C^\infty_{X, x} \arrow[d, "\pi_x", white] \\
    \mathbb{R} \arrow[r, "\mathrm{id}", white] & \mathbb{R}
  \end{tikzcd}
</script> </div> </div> <p>We can see this with the following argument. Note that the map on the stalks \(f^\sharp_x : C^\infty_{Y, f(x)} \to C^\infty_{X, x}\) for any \(x \in X\) is constructed so that it commutes with the sheaf map \(f^\sharp\) via localization. This map then projects down to the identity map on the residue fields since it’s a nonzero map of \(\RR\)-algebras. Then, for any \(h : V \to \RR\) smooth in \(C^\infty_Y(V)\) for \(V\) open, \(f^\sharp(V)(h)(x) = h(f(x))\) along the outside of the commutative diagram, so any morphism is given by precomposition, as desired.</p> <p>This allows us to immediately observe that a smooth map of manifolds \(f : M \to N\) is just given by a continuous map \(f : M \to N\) such that for any \(V \subseteq N\) open and section \(t \in \cOO_N(V)\), then \(t \circ f \in \cOO_M(f^{-1}(V))\) (Proposition 4.18). To see that \(f^\sharp\) is given by pre-composition by \(f\), note that it suffices to check this on any stalk, but then passing to the Euclidean case gives the desired result. Conversely, any continuous map satisfying this condition gives a map of sheaves, since we know that \(\cOO_M\) and \(\cOO_N\) are just the sheaves of smooth maps to \(\RR\) anyway. Note that the same result holds for a map of smooth manifolds defined on charts just by pulling back charts on \(N\) to \(M\), so this indicates that we’re onto something equivalent here!</p> <p>In particular, we can now recover an atlas on \(M\) whose sheaf of smooth real-valued functions is the same as \(\mc O_M = C^\infty_M\)! We can just consider the isomorphisms \(\vphi_i : (U_i, \cOO_M\vert_{U_i}) \to (X_i, C^\infty_{X_i})\) for \(X_i \subseteq \RR^{n_i}\) which induce homeomorphisms \(\vphi_i : U_i \to \RR^n\). Checking these are compatible follows essentially immediately from the fact that \(\vphi_i^{-1}\) is a morphism, and our characterization of morphisms above shows that this gives an atlas. Using these charts to define a sheaf of smooth real-valued functions on \(M\) recovers the original sheaf, so these constructions are in fact equivalent. This shows that we can interpret the category of manifolds as a subcategory of the category of locally ringed spaces! Hooray!</p> <p>I think we can be already be happy with this reframing of a manifold, but I also don’t think this was super impressive. We more or less already had our charts still sitting in our definition, and all we did was did a little trickery to spotlight the sheaf of smooth functions instead. Can we instead do this more algebraically? That is, can we instead take the algebraic structure of \(C^\infty(M)\) itself instead as the “smooth structure” on \(M\) and use it to tell us things about \(M\)?</p> <h3 id="topological-headcanons-for-algebra-enjoyers">topological headcanons for algebra enjoyers</h3> <p>Here things are going to get a little wacky. Rings of real-valued continuous functions \(X \to \RR\) for a general topological space \(X\) can be really strange, so it’s entirely possible that rings of smooth functions might be pretty weird as well. But, as it turns out, these rings of functions hold a lot of information about the space contained in their maximal ideals if \(X\) is “nice enough.” In particular, one can can recover the points of \(X\) and the topology on \(X\), and so this might be another way to get at a manifold without even needing the underlying topological space!</p> <h4 id="general-nonsense">general nonsense</h4> <p>This is actually an exercise (Problem 1.26) in Atiyah-Macdonald<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. Suppose \(X\) is a compact Hausdorff space, and let \(C(X)\) (what one sometimes might call \(C^0(X)\)) be its ring of real-valued continuous functions on \(X\), under pointwise addition/multiplication. (Before you yell at me again, it’s got a multiplicative unit, since the constant function \(1_X\) that evaluates to \(1\) for every point in \(X\) is continuous.)</p> <p>For every point \(x \in X\), we have an ideal of functions \(\mfk m_x = \set{ f \in C(X) : f(x) = 0}\) vanishing at \(x\) (it’s not too hard to see this is an ideal). Note that the evaluation map at a point \(x\), \(\ev_x : C(X) \to \RR\) sending \(f \mapsto f(x)\) is a surjective ring homomorphism, and its kernel is exactly \(\mfk m_x\) by definition. So, by the First Isomorphism Theorem, \(C(X) / \mfk m_x \iso \RR\) so \(\mfk m_x\) is in fact maximal! That’s pretty neat and will become relevant in a second.</p> <p>So far nothing too strange has happened yet, so let’s remember a little bit of algebraic geometry now. Recall that the maximal ideals of \(C(X)\) are points in \(\spec C(X)\), so we might want to consider the subspace of <em>maximal</em> ideals in \(\spec C(X)\). Let’s call this the <em>maximal spectrum</em> of \(C(X)\), \(\maxspec C(X)\) (and similarly for any ring \(A\)). Since this is a subset of \(\spec C(X)\), we can induce the Zariski topology on this subset, so \(\maxspec C(X)\) is a topological space now. And would you believe it, the mapping \(\mu\) from \(X \to \maxspec C(X)\) takind \(x \mapsto \mfk m_x\) turns out not only to be a continuous function between topological spaces, <em>it’s a homeomorphism!</em></p> <p>I think this is really wacky, because the Zariski topology is famously not even Hausdorff. But if this claim is true, this means that sitting inside \(\spec C(X)\), we have a compact Hausdorff space, which is a normal (\(T_4\)) space. Recall that normal spaces are really nice spaces that have tons of nice point-set topological properties. For instance, if a normal space \(X\) happens to also be second-countable, \(X\) now admits a metric by Urysohn’s Metrization Theorem. “Normal” is the adjective I therefore ascribe in my brain to “nice” topological spaces I see in analysis compared to the ones I see in a general point-set topology setting, and thinking about doing analysis to a Zariski thing feels wrong in a way that I can’t really articulate.</p> <p>Anyways, we now we have three things to check to show this claim – we have to check that \(\mu\) is surjective, injective, and continuous with a continuous inverse.</p> <p>We’ll do injectivity quickly first. For any two distinct points \(x, y \in X\), \(x\) and \(y\) are both closed points since \(X\) is Hausdorff, and so by Urysohn’s Lemma (applied to a compact Hausdorff and hence normal space) we know that there is a continuous function \(f : X \to [0, 1]\) with \(f(x) = 0\) and \(f(y) = 1\). This function \(f\) lies in \(\mfk m_x\) but not \(\mfk m_y\), so we see that \(\mfk m_x \neq \mfk m_y\) and hence \(\mu\) is injective.</p> <p>Surjectivity is the trickiest part of the argument, but we’ll do it next. Letting \(\mfk m\) be any maximal ideal of \(C(X)\), we have to realize it as \(\mfk m_x\) for some \(x \in X\). To do this, let’s consider the set \(V = Z(\mfk m) = \set{x \in X : f(x) = 0, f \in \mfk m}\), i.e. the set of common zeroes of the functions in \(\mfk m\). The idea is now that \(V\) has to be non-empty, so we can pick out some \(x \in V\). But then \(\mfk m_x \subseteq \mfk m\), and since \(\mfk m_x\) was maximal, then \(\mfk m_x = \mfk m\), as desired. So we just have to make sure that we can always pick a point out of \(V\).</p> <p>Suppose for the sake of contradiction that \(V\) were empty. If this is the case, then we will be able to find a unit \(g \in \mfk m\), which would be a contradiction because then \(\mfk m = C(X)\). First, for any \(f \in C(X)\), define the sets \(U_f = \set{x \in X : f(x) \neq 0}\). These are open since \(U_f = f^{-1}(\RR - \set 0)\), and they’re the preimage of an open set under a continuous map. We use these to form an open cover of \(X\). For any \(x \in X\), we can find some \(f_x \in \mfk m\) such that \(f_x(x) \neq 0\), so \(U_{f_x}\) is an open set containing \(x\). Clearly, \(X = \bigcup_{x \in X} U_{f_x}\), but then since \(X\) is compact, we can write \(X = \bigcup_{i=1}^n U_{f_{x_i}}\) for finitely many \(x_i \in X\). On this set, the function \(g = \sum_{i=1}^n f_{x_i}^2\) is non-negative and each \(x \in X\) is contained in some \(U_{f_{x_i}}\), on which \(f_{x_i}^2(x) &gt; 0\). This is a unit since \(g &gt; 0\) everywhere on \(X\), and moreover, since each \(f_{x_i} \in \mfk m\), \(g \in \mfk m\). This yields the desired contradiction, so \(V\) could not have been empty.</p> <p>Finally, we have to show that \(\mu\) is continuous with continuous inverse. First, note that the \(U_f\)s form a basis for the topology on \(X\). We can do this using Urysohn’s Lemma again. For any \(U \subseteq X\) open and \(x \in U\), note that \(X - U\) is closed. Then, use Urysohn’s Lemma to construct a continuous function \(f_x\) such that \(f_x(x) = 1\) and \(f_x(X - U) = 0\). This makes \(U_{f_x} \subseteq U\) and contain \(x \in U\), so then \(U = \bigcup_{x \in U} U_{f_x}\) and therefore \(U\) is a union of these basic open sets.</p> <p>Now, recall in the Zariski topology on \(\maxspec C(X)\), for any \(f \in C(X)\), the set \(D_f = \set{\mfk m \in \maxspec X : f \not \in \mfk m}\) is a basic open set by construction. Now, we check that \(\mu(U_f) = D_f\) for any \(f \in C(X)\). This follows since if \(x \in U_f\), \(f(x) \neq 0\). Then, \(\mfk m_x = \set{g \in C(X) : g(x) = 0}\), so \(f \not \in \mfk m_x\). This shows that \(\mu(x) = \mfk m_x \in D_f\). Conversely, given that \(\mu\) is surjective, write \(\mfk m = \mfk m_x \in D_f\) for some \(x \in X\). Since \(f \not \in \mfk m_x\), \(f(x) \neq 0\), so then \(x \in U_f\). This means that \(\mfk m = \mfk m_x \in \mu(U_f)\), which shows the sets are equal. Now, since \(\mu\) is a bijection, the preimage of any basic open set \(D_f\) under \(\mu\) is \(U_f\) open, so \(\mu\) is continuous. Moreover, \(\mu\) is clearly open-mapping since we just checked this on a basis, so \(\mu\) is a homeomorphism, as desired.</p> <p>Shockingly, this means that \(C(X)\) completely determines the underlying space \(X\) if \(X\) is compact Hausdorff! Since \(X\) is homeomorphic to \(\maxspec C(X)\), if \(C(X) \iso C(Y)\) for some other compact Hausdorff space \(Y\), then necessarily \(X \iso Y\).</p> <p>This is pretty cool! Note that we technically didn’t need the full power of Urysohn’s Lemma in this argument – we just needed that \(X\) was <em>completely regular</em>, i.e. has the property that points in \(X\) can be separated from closed sets by continuous real-valued functions. In particular, the comments of this <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1459801/can-we-recover-a-space-from-its-continuous-functions/1459811#1459811">stackexchange answer</a> indicate that one can again reconstruct the topology on \(X\) if \(X\) is just Hausdorff and completely regular (i.e. <em>Tychonoff</em>). The thread is a little confusing on whether one can actually determine \(X\) uniquely up to isomorphism, but the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tychonoff_space#Real-valued_continuous_functions">Wikipedia page for Tychonoff spaces</a> indicates that you probably want \(X\) to be something called <em>realcompact</em> also to make this true. In particular, in this case, you actually get the stronger result that if \(X\) and \(Y\) are spaces that are both Tychonoff and realcompact, then there is a bijection between \(\hom(X,Y)\) and \(\hom(C(Y), C(X))\). In particular, there is an anti-equivalence of categories between the category of these spaces and the corresponding category of rings of continuous functions on these spaces. It’s a little unclear to me whether or not this is stronger/weaker than being compact Hausdorff, but I’m no general topologist…</p> <h4 id="ok-but-thats-not-a-manifold-though">ok but that’s not a manifold though</h4> <p>fine. We can pursue the above further, but the main point of the exercise above is to indicate that something similar might also work in the case of a smooth manifold, but now we have smooth functions which are also probably nicer. Let’s specialize to the case of a smooth manifold \(M\) and run a similar argument to show that one can recover \(M\) from \(C^\infty(M)\) for any manifold \(M\). The following outline for the argument comes as an exercise from <em>Characteristic Classes</em> by Milnor and Stasheff (Problem 1C) and these <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1577985/smooth-manifold-m-is-completely-determined-by-the-ring-f">stackexchange</a> <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1764947/can-we-recover-a-compact-smooth-manifold-from-its-ring-of-smooth-functions">posts</a>.</p> <p>The argument proceeds very similarly. Note that again that \(C^\infty(M)\) is an \(\RR\)-algebra with a unit \(1_M\), the constant function on \(M\). Here, we will want to consider ring homomorphisms \(\vphi : C^\infty(M) \to \RR\), and we claim that \(\vphi\) extends to an \(\RR\)-algebra homomorphism. To do this, we need to establish a few properties about any such ring homomorphism \(\vphi\).</p> <p>First, for an arbitrary function \(f \in C^\infty(M)\), if \(f &gt; 0\), then \(\vphi(f) &gt; 0\). \(\vphi(f) \neq 0\) since \(\frac 1f \in C^\infty(M)\) as \(f\) vanishes nowhere, so \(\vphi(f)\) is a unit in \(\RR\), i.e. not zero. Then, \(\sqrt f \in C^\infty (M)\), so \(\vphi(f) = \vphi(\sqrt f)^2 \geq 0\), and therefore \(\vphi(f) &gt; 0\) since it is not zero. Next, from the fact that \(\vphi(1_M) = 1\), we can get \(\vphi(q 1_M) = q\) for any \(q \in \QQ\). Then, \(\vphi\) extends to a \(\QQ\)-algebra homomorphism, since</p> \[\vphi(q f) = \vphi(q 1_M \cdot f) = \vphi(q 1_M) \vphi(f) = q \vphi(f).\] <p>To boost this to an \(\RR\)-algebra homomorphism, we must show that \(\vphi\) preserves order on the copy of \(\RR \iso \RR 1_M \subseteq C^\infty(M)\). To see this, note that for any \(a &gt; b \in \RR\), \((a-b) 1_M &gt; 0\), so \(\vphi(a 1_M - b 1_M) &gt; 0\) and therefore \(\vphi(a 1_M) &gt; \vphi(b 1_M)\). If WLOG for some \(r \in \RR\) we had that \(\vphi(r 1_M) &gt; r\), find some \(q \in \QQ\) with \(r &lt; q &lt; \vphi(r)\). Then \(\vphi(q1_M - r1_M) &gt; 0\), but this is also equal to \(\vphi(q1_M) - \vphi(r1_M) = q - \vphi(r1_M) &lt; 0\), contradiction. A similar argument shows that \(\vphi(r1_M)\) is not less than \(r\) either, so it must be equal to \(r\). Now the same argument as above extending \(\vphi\) to a \(\QQ\)-algebra homomorphism allows us to extend \(\vphi\) to an \(\RR\)-algebra homomorphism. As such, ring homomorphisms and \(\RR\)-algebra homomorphisms \(C^\infty(M) \to \RR\) are equivalent, which will be nice to allow us to conflate the two as needed.</p> <p>Now, similar to the above, define an \(\RR\)-algebra homomorphism \(\ev_x : C^\infty(M) \to \RR\) for any \(x \in M\) that just evaluates a function at \(x\), i.e. \(f \mapsto f(x)\). As above, the set \(\mfk m_x = \set{f \in C^\infty(M) : f(x) = 0}\) is an ideal and is equal to \(\ker \ev_x\), and since \(\ev_x\) is surjective, \(C^\infty(M) / \mfk m_x \iso \RR\) and therefore \(\mfk m_x\) is maximal. Now, in this case, we show that <em>every ring homomorphism</em> \(\vphi : C^\infty(M) \to \RR\) is given by an evaluation map, using a method similar to the above.</p> <p>Suppose that some homomorphism \(\vphi\) is not given by an evaluation map \(\ev_x\) for some \(x \in M\). Then, for every \(x \in M\), there is some function \(f_x \in C^\infty(M)\) with \(\vphi(f_x) \neq f_x(x)\). If we are given a compact set \(K \subseteq M\), we will show that we can construct some element \(F_K \in C^\infty(M)\) where \(\vphi(F_K) = 0\), but \(F_K \geq 0\) everywhere and is guaranteed to satisfy \(F_K &gt; 0\) on \(K\). To do this, note that \(F_x = (f_x - \vphi(f_x) 1_M)^2\) for any \(x \in M\) gives us a start at this. Observe</p> \[\vphi(F_x) = \vphi((f_x - \vphi(f_x) 1_M)^2) = \vphi(f_x - \vphi(f_x) 1_M)^2 = (\vphi(f_x) - \vphi(f_x))^2 = 0\] <p>and clearly \(F_x \geq 0\). Moreover, at \(x\), \(F_x(x) = (f_x - \vphi(f_x) 1_M)^2(x) = (f_x(x) - \vphi(f_x))^2 &gt; 0\). Then, take the open sets \(U_x = F_x^{-1}(0, \infty)\), each of which contains \(x\) by constuction. Use these open sets to form an open cover of \(K\) using by \(K = \bigcup_{x \in K}U_x\), but now since \(K\) is compact, \(K = \bigcup_{i=1}^n U_{x_i}\) for finitely many \(x_i \in K\). Then \(F_K = \sum_{i=1}^n F_{x_i}\) works. Note \(\vphi(F_K) = \sum_{i=1}^n \vphi(F_{x_i}) = 0\), and \(F_K\) is non-negative since it is a sum of non-negative functions. Finally, since for any \(x \in K\), \(x \in U_{x_i}\) for some \(i\), \(F_{x_i}(x) &gt; 0\) for this \(i\), and so \(F_K(x) &gt; 0\) since each \(F_{x_i}\) is at least non-negative.</p> <p>But how do we get such a \(K\) to work with? Since \(M\) is no longer compact, we need to use a <em>partition of unity</em> of \(M\) to concoct a similar argument as in the compact case using finiteness. In particular, we will going to pick a partition of unity indexed by a countable set \(\set{\rho_i}_{i=1}^\infty\), with each \(\supp \rho_i\) compact.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> Then, let’s consider the function \(h = \sum_{i=1}^\infty i \rho_i\). This function is well-defined since \(\set{\supp \rho_i}_{i=1}^\infty\) is locally finite, and so in any neighborhood of a point \(x \in M\), \(h\) is locally a finite sum of smooth functions, so \(h\) is smooth and an element of \(C^\infty(M)\). Moreover, \(h\) will give us a compact subset of \(M\) by observing that \(h^{-1}([0, c])\) for any \(c \in \RR\) will be compact. In particular, \(h^{-1}([0, c]) \subseteq \bigcup_{i=1}^{\floor c} \supp \rho_i\), so it’ll be compact as it is a closed subset of a compact set. To see this, if a point \(x \not \in \bigcup_{i=1}^{\floor c} \supp \rho_i\), then</p> \[h(x) = \sum_{i=1}^\infty i \rho_i(x) = \sum_{i = \floor c + 1} i \rho_i(x) \geq (\floor c + 1) \sum_{i=1}^\infty \rho_i(x) = (\floor c + 1).\] <p>so \(x \not \in h^{-1}([0,c])\). Such an \(h\) constructed in this way will soon be critical in building our contradiction.</p> <p>Our contradiction, as in the previous case, will be the construction of a badly-behaved smooth function that will again be a unit but vanishes under \(\vphi\). First, let \(h\) be as obtained above from the partition of unity and note that \(h &gt; 1_M\), so it is non-negative. Let \(c = \vphi(h)\). Then, \(K = h^{-1}([0,c])\) is compact, and we can obtain an \(F_K\) non-negative everywhere with \(\vphi(F_K) = 0\) and \(F_K &gt; 0\) on \(K\). In particular, since \(K\) is compact, \(F_K\) achieves some minimum value \(m &gt; 0\) on \(K\). Then, \((\frac 1m + 1) F_K &gt; 1_M\) on \(K\) by construction, is still non-negative, and still satisfies \(\vphi((\frac 1m + 1) F_K) = 0\). Now, consider the function \(g = h + c(\frac 1m + 1) F_K - c1_M\). First, note that \(g\) is strictly positive everywhere. For a point \(x \in K\), since \(h &gt; 0\) and \(c(\frac 1m + 1) F_K - c 1_M &gt; c1_M - c1_M = 0\) by construction, \(g(x) &gt; 0\). If \(x \not \in K = h^{-1}([0, c])\), then \(h(x) &gt; c\) since \(h(x) &gt; 0\), so \(h(x) - c &gt; 0\). Then, since \(c(\frac 1m +1)F_K &gt; 0\), \(g(x) &gt; 0\) again, so \(g\) is strictly positive everywhere. As we proved at the very start of this section, this means that \(g\) should be a unit. However,</p> \[\vphi(g) = \vphi(h) + \vphi\left(c \left(\frac 1m + 1\right) F_K\right) - \vphi(c 1_M) = c + 0 - c = 0,\] <p>contradiction. Hooray!</p> <p>Wait, what did this prove again? We’ve now shown that <em>every</em> ring homomorphism \(C^\infty(M) \to \RR\) is given by \(\ev_x\) for some \(x \in M\). This means that \(\hat M = \hom_{Ring}(C^\infty(M), \RR)\) is in bijection with the points of \(M\) (again, using a smooth version of the Urysohn Lemma with bump functions, sending a point \(x \in M\) to \(\ev_x\) is injective). This gives us a <em>lot</em> of hope for now being able to reconstruct the manifold’s topological/smooth structure, since we’ve now been able to algebraically describe the manifold’s points.</p> <p>While our strategy was pretty similar as to the case of \(C(X)\), it seems like our characterization of points is now no longer in terms of nice (in the last case, maximal) ideals, and is instead in terms of ring/\(\RR\)-algebra homomorphisms \(C^\infty(M) \to \RR\). However, we can canonically force ourselves to think in terms of ideals if we want to. Since all such \(\RR\)-algebra homomorphisms are surjective, the kernel of any such homomorphism \(\vphi : C^\infty(M) \to \RR\) is again maximal, since \(C^\infty(M) / \ker \vphi \iso \RR\). This at least gives a partial characterization of the points of \(M\) in terms of the ideals of \(C^\infty(M)\).</p> <h3 id="spicy-lee-fanfiction">spicy Lee fanfiction</h3> <p>It feels like that if we really wanted to do algebraic geometry to a manifold, we should treat the points of a manifold described above as a particular subset of the maximal ideals of its ring of smooth functions. Unfortunately, there is a problem with this – maximal ideals don’t behave very functorially, since the preimage of a maximal ideal under a ring homomorphism need not be maximal. Regardless, the idea that points of a manifold correspond to \(\RR\)-algebra homomorphisms to \(\RR\), when dualized to spectra of rings, is kind of reminiscent of the idea of an \(\RR\)-point on a scheme! This will end up being the right idea to pursue if we want to think about a manifold purely in terms of algebra.</p> <h4 id="ending-the-story-arc">ending the story arc</h4> <p>But first, we should finish our algebraic reconstruction of a manifold \(M\) – we’ve so far been able to characterize the points in terms of \(C^\infty(M)\), but \(M\) also has a topology and a smooth structure (either of the sheaf-of-smooth-functions variety or of the atlas variety) that we still need to reconstruct. How do we get this from \(C^\infty(M)\)?</p> <p>Since the smooth real-valued functions on \(M\) are the elements of \(C^\infty(M)\), and we are currently thinking of the points of \(\hat M = \hom(C^\infty(M), \RR)\) as the points of \(M\), we should again use \(C^\infty(M)\) to tell us topological information about \(M\). In particular, we need to think about a way to use an element \(f \in C^\infty(M)\) to define a map \(\hat M \to \RR\). Well, there’s kind of an obvious construction of such a map \(\hat f\) for any \(f \in C^\infty(M)\), just by taking \(\hat f (\ev_x) = f(x)\). We want to eventually think of \(\hat f\) as smooth, so surely we should at least make it continuous! Then, the natural way to define a topology on \(\hat M\) is to just pick the “coarsest one making the \(\hat f\)s continuous.”</p> <p>Now, if you’re familiar with functional analysis, this might sound familiar. Thinking of \(C^\infty(M)\) and \(\hat M\) as \(\RR\)-vector spaces, think about the canonical bilinear pairing of \(\RR\)-vector spaces \(\ev : \hat M \times C^\infty(M) \to \RR\) by \(\ev(\ev_x, f) = f(x)\). Now, the topology we just defined on \(\hat M\) is just the <em>weak topology</em>!<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> hooray functional analysis!</p> <p>Does this topology on \(\hat M\) make it homeomorphic to \(M\) though? We’ve seen the map \(\mu : M \to \hat M\) sending \(x \mapsto \ev_x\) is a bijection, but we need to check that it is continuous and closed-mapping. We know the only open sets in the topology on \(\hat M\) are the exactly the ones needed to make any map \(\hat f\) continuous, so in particular the open sets are of the form \((\hat f)^{-1}(U)\) for some \(U \subseteq \RR\). We now want to check that \(\mu^{-1}((\hat f)^{-1}(U))\) is open in \(M\). Note that this preimage is really just \((\hat f \circ \mu)^{-1}(U)\), and wait, the map \(\hat f \circ \mu\) sends a point \(x \in M\) to \(f(x)\), so \(\hat f \circ \mu = f\). But \(f\) is continuous since it’s smooth, so \(\mu\) is continuous.</p> <p>The only other thing we need to see is that \(\mu\) sends closed sets to closed sets. Suppose \(K\) is a proper closed subset of \(M\). Using the smooth version of Urysohn’s Lemma again, we can construct a smooth function \(f : M \to [0, 1]\) such that \(f\vert_K = 0\) (and \(f(x) = 1\) for some point \(x \not \in K\)). Now, \(\mu(K) = \set{ \ev_x : x \in K}\), and by the construction of this \(f\), \(f(K) = (\hat f \circ \mu)(K) = \set 0\), so \(\mu(K) = (\hat f)^{-1}(\set 0)\). Since \(\hat f\) is continuous, \(\mu(K)\) is closed, so \(\mu\) is now also closed-mapping. Since \(\mu\) is a bijection, \(\mu\) is also open-mapping, so its inverse is continuous. Therefore, \(\mu\) is a homeomorphism!</p> <p>Finally, we need to reconstruct the smooth structure on \(\hat M\), which we now identify with \(M\). Since we literally have the smooth global sections \(C^\infty(M)\) as given, it seems like the right thing to do is to just define a sheaf of real-valued smooth functions on \(\hat M\) isomorphic to the sheaf of real-valued smooth functions on \(M\) under mapping by \(\mu\). We will do this by first constructing a suitable presheaf \(\mc S\) on \(\hat M = M\). (We’re only doing this identification in order to be able to compare sheaves on the same base space. However, throughout the following we are going to be super careful to make sure that anything we construct will be purely in terms of things we’ve constructed already, so some of our maps will look a little strange in order for them to actually make sense on the level of sets.)</p> <p>First, we already have a candidate for the ring of global sections on \(\hat M\) – we can consider the \(\RR\)-algebra that we denote by \(\mc S(M) = \set{\hat f : f \in C^\infty(M)}\). In order to have any hope at making \(\mc S\) produce the right sheaf, we have to at least have \(C^\infty(M) \iso \mc S(M)\). Well, we at least have a natural surjective homomorphism \(\mu^\sharp : C^\infty(M) \to \mc S(M)\) sending \(f \mapsto \hat f\). This map is also injective – if \(f \in \ker \mu^\sharp\), then \(\hat f (\ev_x) = 0\) for any \(x \in M\), but then this implies that \(f(x) = 0\), so \(f = 0\). Therefore, \(\mu^\sharp\) is an isomorphism.</p> <p>Now, we can define \(\mc S(U)\) for any \(U \subseteq M\) in the obvious way. Using the inclusion \(i_U : \mu(U) \to \hat M\) corresponding to the inclusion \(U \to M\), take \(\mc S(U) = \set{ \hat f \circ i_U : \hat f \in \mc S(\hat M)}\). In particular, any restriction map should correspond to precomposing by the appropriate inclusion of open sets, which automatically gives a presheaf. We can’t really demand that \(\mu^\sharp\) descends to a morphism of presheaves though, because locally on \(M\), we can have smooth functions that don’t extend globally to a smooth function everywhere. However, we can define a morphism \(\nu : \mc S \to C^\infty_M\) by taking \(\nu(U) : \mc S(U) \to C^\infty_M(U)\) to be given by precomposing by \(\mu\).</p> <p>Now, we can use \(\mc S\) to recover \(C^\infty_M\). Again asking \(\mc S\) to be isomorphic to \(C^\infty_M\) isn’t going to work, again because of local-to-global issues. But, we claim that we have an isomorphism of sheaves \(\nu^+ : \mc S^+ \to C^\infty_M\), where \(\mc S^+\) is the sheafification of \(\mc S\). To construct this isomorphism, we use the morphism \(\nu\) defined above and show that for every \(x \in M\), \(\nu_x : \mc S_x \to C^\infty_{M,x}\) is an isomorphism. Then, we can finish by using the universal property of the sheafification to get our desired isomorphism \(\mc S^+ \to C^\infty_M\).</p> <p>Recall that the stalks of a (pre)sheaf \(\mc F\) at a point \(x \in M\) are given by germs of sections at \(x\), i.e. \(\mc F_x = \set{(U, s) : x \in U \text{ open} \subseteq M, s \in \mc F(U)} / \sim\), where \(\sim\) is an equivalence relation generated by \((U_1, s_1) \sim (U_2, s_2)\) if \(s_1 \vert_V = s_2 \vert_V\) for some open \(V \subseteq U_1 \cap U_2\). Then \(\nu_x\) maps \([U, \hat f \circ i_U]\) to \([U, \nu(U)(\hat f \circ i_U)] = [U, \hat f \circ i_U \circ \mu]\), i.e. it acts by \(\nu\) on the section. To construct an inverse, we need a bump function \(\rho\) with \(x \in \supp \rho \subseteq U\), so that any smooth map \(f : U \to \RR\) can be extended to \(f \rho : M \to \RR\). Then we can construct the map \(\nu_x^{-1} : C^\infty_{M, x} \to \mc S^+\) via \([U, f] \mapsto [U, \widehat{f\rho} \circ i_U]\). To check that this is well-defined, suppose we had some other representative \([V, g] = [U, f]\), and we need to show that \([V, \widehat{g\rho} \circ i_V] = [U, \widehat{f\rho} \circ i_U]\). Note that since \(f\) and \(g\) agree on some open \(W \subseteq U \cap V\) containing \(x\), \(g\rho = f\rho\) on \(W\) as well. Then, \(\widehat{g\rho} = \widehat{f\rho}\) on \(\mu(W)\), so these germs are the same as these functions agree on \(\mu(W)\), so phew! \(\nu_x^{-1}\) is well-defined as a function.</p> <p>Now, it’s clear by construction that \(\nu_x^{-1}\) is a homomorphism of \(\RR\)-algebras, so we only have to check that it’s an inverse to \(\nu_x\). Throughout, let \(V \subseteq U\) be the open set where \(\rho = 1\). To see this last step through, we first check that \(\nu_x^{-1} \circ \nu_x\) is the identity. If we pick some \([U, \hat f \circ i_U] \in \mc S(U)\) for some \(f \in C^\infty(M)\), then \(\nu_x^{-1}([U, \hat f \circ i_U \circ \mu])\) simplifies to \([U, \widehat{(\hat f \circ i_U \circ \mu) \rho} \circ i_U]\). We want this to be the same germ as \([U, \hat f \circ i_U]\), and in particular we claim these agree on \(\mu(V)\). For any \(y \in V\), \((\hat f \circ i_U)(\ev_y) = f(y)\). On the other hand, evaluating at \(\ev_y\), we unravel definitions to see that</p> \[(\widehat{(\hat f \circ i_U \circ \mu) \rho} \circ i_U)(\ev_y) = ((\hat f \circ i_U \circ \mu)\rho)(y) = (\hat f \circ i_U)(\ev_y) = f(y)\] <p>so these are both the same germ \([V, \hat f \circ i_V]\). Next, to check \(\nu_x \circ \nu_x^{-1}\) is the identity, for any \(f : U \to \RR\), we also claim that \(\widehat{f\rho} \circ i_U \circ \mu\) agrees with \(f\) on \(V\). This is an easier computation – for \(y \in V\),</p> \[(\widehat{f\rho} \circ i_U \circ \mu)(y) = (\widehat{f\rho}\circ i_U)(\ev_y) = (f\rho)(y) = f(y)\] <p>so indeed \(\nu_x\) is an isomorphism. By the argument above, this shows that the sheafification of \(\mc S\) recovers the smooth structure of \(M\)! In particular, if we have for manifolds \(M\) and \(N\) that \(C^\infty(M) \iso C^\infty(N)\), we have now shown that \(M \iso N\). The ring of smooth functions on a manifold therefore determines the entire manifold \(M\), its topological structure, and its smooth structure!</p> <p>We can also talk about translating smooth maps into this setting. We already basically did this earlier though – a smooth map of manifolds \(\vphi : M \to N\) yields a map on their sheaves of smooth real-valued functions. In particular, we have a map of \(\RR\)-algebras \(\vphi^* : C^\infty(N) \to C^\infty(M)\) given by \(g \mapsto g \circ \vphi\). This also lifts to a map \(\vphi^{**} : \hat M \to \hat N\) given by \(\ev_x \mapsto \ev_x \circ \vphi^*\). In particular, \(\vphi^{**}\) commutes with the homeomorphism \(\mu_M : M \to \hat M\) in a nice way, so that \(\vphi^{**} \circ \mu_M = \mu_N \circ \vphi\). To see this, for any \(x \in M\), note that \((\mu_N \circ \vphi)(x) = \ev_{\vphi(x)}\), and \(\vphi^{**}(\ev_x) = \ev_x \circ \vphi^*\). On a function \(g \in C^\infty(N)\),</p> \[(\ev_x \circ \vphi^*)(g) = \ev_x \circ (g \circ \vphi) = g(\vphi(x)) = \ev_{\vphi(x)}(g)\] <p>so this equality holds.</p> <p>Conversely, suppose we had a map of \(\RR\)-algebras \(\psi : C^\infty(N) \to C^\infty(M)\). As above, this yields a map \(\psi^* : \hat M \to \hat N\) given by \(\ev_x \mapsto \ev_x \circ \psi\). Taking global sections \(\mc S^+\) of these spaces, note that under the sheafification \(\mc S^+(M) \iso \mc S (M)\), which we now identify. Also, any \(\psi^*\) induces a map \(\psi^{**} : \mc S(N) \to \mc S(M)\) given by \(\hat g \mapsto \hat g \circ \psi^*\). Recall the isomorphism \(\mu^\sharp_M : C^\infty(M) \to \mc S(M)\) that precomposes by the homeomorphism \(\mu_M : M \to \hat M\). Then \(\psi^{**}\) also commutes with respect to this isomorphism, i.e. \(\psi^{**} \circ \mu^\sharp_N = \mu_M^\sharp \circ \psi\). To see this, pick a \(g \in C^\infty(N)\) again, and observe that \((\mu_M^\sharp \circ \psi)(g) = \psi(g) \circ \mu_M^{-1}\), and</p> \[(\psi^{**} \circ \mu^\sharp_N)(g) = \psi^{**}(g \circ \mu_N^{-1}) = \psi^{**}(\hat g) = \hat g \circ \psi^* = g \circ \mu_N^{-1} \circ \psi^*\] <p>To see this is equal to \(\psi(g) \circ \mu_M\), pick an \(x \in M\) and thereby an \(\ev_x \in \hat M\). Then we can evaluate this and get \((\psi(g) \circ \mu_M^{-1})(\ev_x) = \psi(g)(x)\). Similarly, \((g \circ \mu_N^{-1} \circ \psi^*)(\ev_x) = (g \circ \mu_N^{-1})(\ev_x \circ \psi)\). Now, \(\ev_x \circ \psi = \ev_y\) for some \(y \in N\), which allows us to rearrange a bit to get</p> \[(g \circ \mu_N^{-1})(\ev_y) = g(y) = \ev_y(g) = \ev_x \circ \psi \circ g = \psi(g)(x) .\] <p>This allows us to show that inducing a map on global sections from a smooth function and inducing a smooth map from a map on global sections are inverses, which tells us there is a bijection</p> \[\hom(M, N) \to \hom(C^\infty(N), C^\infty(M)).\] <p>This looks an awful lot like the the categorical anti-equivalence between affine schemes and rings – in this case, we have a categorical equivalence between manifolds and “\(\RR\)-algebras that look like \(C^\infty(M)\).” In particular, a manifold is some subset of \(\spec C^\infty(M)\), if we choose to think about the kernels of the maps in \(\hom(C^\infty(M), \RR)\) instead. Also, as we saw in the reconstruction of the topology on \(M\), every closed subset is a zero-locus of some smooth function by Urysohn’s Lemma, so in particular this topology is at least as fine as the Zariski topology on \(\spec C^\infty(M)\). This seems to indicate that we could really define a manifold instead via spectra of rings, as in schemes…</p> <h4 id="my-favorite-fanfiction">my favorite fanfiction</h4> <p>The above arguments were heavily inspired/directly come from Chapter 2 of <em>\(C^\infty\)-Differentiable Spaces</em> by Juan A. Navarro González and Juan B. Sancho de Salas, Chapters 3 and 7 of <em>Smooth Manifolds and Observables</em> by Jet Nestruev, and this <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/q/2947100">stackexchange answer</a>. At this point, I’d like to honor the approaches laid out in these books that basically argue what I have here in a much more straightforward fashion.</p> <p>The approach of González and Sancho de Salas is to really think about a manifold as a kind of a spectrum in some sense. In particular, given a unital commutative \(\RR\)-algebra \(A\) giving a canonical homomorphism \(\RR \to A\), we say an ideal \(\mfk m \subseteq A\) is <em>real</em> if the composition with the quotient \(\RR \to A / \mfk m\) is an isomorphism. The collection of real ideals (which must all be maximal) is called the <em>real spectrum</em> of \(A\), \(\spec_\RR A\). This now solves our functoriality problem, because the preimage of a real ideal is indeed real under an \(\RR\)-algebra homomorphism. In algebraic geometry language, what we are really doing is restricting to the \(\RR\)-points of \(\spec C^\infty (M)\), which I think means the points whose residue field is \(\RR\)? I’m not quite familiar enough with algebraic geometry to be confident on this point.</p> <p>For any \(f\) in \(A\), if we think about points of the real spectrum as maximal ideals, we can also see that \(f\) defines a real-valued function on \(A\) by passing to the quotient \(A / \mfk m \iso \RR\). As we did above, we topologize \(\spec_\RR A\) with what the book calls the <em>Gelfand topology,</em> i.e. the coarsest one that makes these maps on \(\spec_\RR A\) for any \(f\) continuous. If \(A\) is the algebra of global sections of a manifold, the book remarks that the Zariski topology on \(\spec_\RR A\) coincides with this, using the smooth version of Urysohn’s Lemma.</p> <p>In general, the book goes on to talk about <em>differentiable algebras</em>, which are suitable quotients of \(C^\infty(\RR^n)\) by an ideal, and <em>differentiable spaces</em>, which are the analogues of rings and schemes in algebraic geometry. Differentiable spaces (as you might guess) are locally isomorphic to spaces called <em>affine differentiable spaces,</em> which are the real spectra of differentiable algebras. A lot of smooth manifold theory/ideas can be replicated in the realm of differentiable spaces, where a lot of the same arguments just kind of go through in very similar ways, but with a sprinkling of what look to me like functional analysis tools and some algebraic geometry ethos.</p> <p>On the other hand, the approach of Nestruev<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup> is very similar, but is more focused on developing smooth manifold theory in a spectral way starting with the algebra smooth functions on a manifold. In particular, they restrict their attentions to a very specific class of \(\RR\)-algebras from which one can construct a manifold in the usual sense. As above, for an \(\RR\)-algebra \(A\), their manifolds are spaces of \(\RR\)-algebra homomorphisms \(A \to \RR\), and they build up the constraints on algebras needed to characterize rings of smooth functions and pull out a manifold. This is not at all an easy task and this, along with developing manifold theory from this point of view, is the bulk of a book.</p> <p>Nestruev requires a “suitable” \(\RR\)-algebra to be <em>geometrical</em>, <em>complete</em>, and <em>smooth</em>. These names are a little mysterious to me, but they arise sort of naturally over the course of Chapters 3/4:</p> <p>First, an algebra \(A\) is <em>geometrical</em> if \(\bigcap_{\vphi \in \hom(A, \RR)} \ker \vphi = 0\). To see why this is important, we need to think for a moment about \(\tilde A = \set{\tilde f : \hom(A, \RR) \to \RR : \tilde f(x) = x(f)}\), where \(x\) denotes an element of \(\hom(A, \RR)\). Here, \(x\) is meant to be the analogue of \(\ev_x\) above, and \(\tilde A\) is the analogue of the global sections \(\mc S(M)\) that we were thinking about. It was important in defining our presheaf \(\mc S\) and showing the eventual categorical equivalence that \(\mc S(M)\) was isomorphic to \(C^\infty(M)\). Here, Nestruev wants in general for \(A\) to be isomorphic to \(\tilde A\), but we can only enforce this if the above kernel condition is satisfied. The “geometrical” nature of this property feels like it comes from the idea that points of the dual \(\hom(A, \RR)\) should be like evaluating at points of the manifold, and if a function vanishes when evaluating algebraically at a point, it should be globally zero. This also feels like it maybe has to do with reducedness of a scheme, maybe. Anyways, after introducing the Gelfand topology on the dual space \(\hom(A, \RR)\), Nestruev is already able to show that it is Hausdorff and that this space recovers \(U \subseteq \RR^n\) open in the case of \(A = C^\infty(U)\).</p> <p>The next thing we need to think about has to do with the sheaf of smooth functions on our space. Nestruev defines a notion of <em>restriction</em> of a geometrical algebra \(A\) to any subset \(K \subseteq \hom(A, \RR)\) as the set of functions \(f: K \to \RR\) such that for any point \(x \in K\), there is an open neighborhood \(U \subseteq K\) and an element \(\overline f \in A\) such that \(f\) and \(\overline f\) are equal on \(U\). Here, \(\overline f\) should be thought of as a function on \(\hom(A, \RR)\) because of the geometrical constraint, and as such this operation can be thought of as a topological restriction. This is a bit of a generalized version of how we defined the presheaf of smooth functions on our constructed space \(\hat M\). Recall that we couldn’t get a whole sheaf of smooth functions because not all smooth functions on an open set extend to a larger one, and therefore we were missing smooth functions in our presheaf.</p> <p>This now brings us to our second constraint. A geometrical algebra \(A\) is <em>complete</em> if the restriction map \(\rho : A \to A\vert_{\hom(A, \RR)}\) is surjective. This feels like constraining \(A\) to now include all of necessary smooth functions on \(\hom(A, \RR)\) to make \(A\) into a sheaf with these restriction maps, which is something that we solved with sheafification. I’m not sure why this is called “complete” though. Maybe \(A\) is just complete in the “there are enough smooth functions” sense?</p> <p>Finally, the last condition required encodes second-countability and the fact that the space is locally Euclidean in one go. A complete geometrical algebra \(A\) is <em>smooth</em> if there is a finite or countable open covering \(\set{U_k}\) of \(\hom(A, \RR)\) such that all of the algebras \(A\vert_{U_k}\) are isomorphic to the algebra of smooth functions \(C^\infty(\RR^n)\). This now recovers all of the properties of a smooth manifold we want. An interesting thing about this property of an algebra \(A\) is that it now requires \(A\) to be <em>closed with respect to smooth composition</em>. This means that for any finite collection of elements \(f_1, \dots, f_k \in A\) and \(g \in C^\infty(\RR^k)\), there is an \(f \in A\) such that \(f(a) = g(f_1(a), \dots, f_k(a))\) for all \(a \in \hom(A, \RR)\). This finaly property feels useful as a purely algebraic constraint that doesn’t really bring in topology at all.</p> <p>These three conditions are then spun out into developing a theory of manifolds in terms of the dual spaces of these algebras, but interestingly using the idea of charts on a manifold rather than sheaves and locally ringed spaces. This feels better pedagogically as a possibly introductory book to the subject, but it does seem a little clunkier in some respects. Also, while spectra are mentioned, they stop just short of providing the correct fix as in González-Sancho de Salas to do things from an algebraic-geometrical perspective. However, they seem to be able to do a lot of cool cohomological stuff and other manifolds-related content later, which I haven’t looked at much and seems cool when done form this perspective.</p> <p>A combination of the approaches from these two sources feels like it adequately bridges the gap between the chart-based intuition for manifolds that I had before and the modern sheaf/locally ringed space perspective that algebraic geometry embraces. I personally think that seeing this connection places the manifold in concert with the other geometric structures that I’ve now seen, but there are major drawbacks to taking this approach. For one, manifolds are too nice to be handled in this way – going from local-to-global is easy (and should be easy!) with a partition of unity, and as such the full power of a sheaf isn’t really needed to keep track of all the data coming from sections. Also, it feels like the niceness of doing things with linear algebra and calculus was all lost, and replacing it with algebra had us working with strange but very cool rings.</p> <p>Also, we haven’t at all been able to translate structures defined on manifolds, which are arguably also important to the study of manifolds and differential geometry. In particular, we don’t have a good notion of vector bundles or differential forms on a manifold, and it’s not quite clear to me how exactly to algebraically encode those kinds of structures. But for now, being able to see manifolds on the same level as other geometric spaces feels good to have done once.</p> <h3 id="coda-how-deep-does-the-rabbit-hole-go">coda: how deep does the rabbit hole go?</h3> <p>While searching for sources to consult to answer this question, here are some extra odds and ends that I thought were cool/relevant but couldn’t fit in:</p> <p>Recall that when we were thinking about manifolds as a locally ringed spaces of \(\RR\)-algebras, locally isomorphic to the smooth functions on \(\RR^n\), we enforced the constraint that our manifolds had to have their underlying topological spaces be Hausdorff and second-countable. This <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/88056/is-there-a-sheaf-theoretical-characterization-of-a-differentiable-manifold">stackexchange post</a> discusses whether it’s possible to drop Hausdorff and second-countable from the constraints on the topological space and encode them in the sheaf itself. It turns out you can, but it seems kind of more annoying than you’d like and translating topological properties into sheaf properties is probably more pain than it’s worth.</p> <p>We also wondered what might happen if you used a different structure sheaf for \(\RR^n\) to induce a sheaf on your topological space. This <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/431642/do-rings-of-smooth-functions-differ-from-rings-of-continuous-functions">stackexchange post</a> asks about rings of continuous functions and if they behave as nicely as the ring of smooth functions. In short – nope! Unlike how one can recover the tangent space<sup id="fnref:3:1"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> from the sheaf of rings of smooth functions on a manifold by thinking about \(\mfk m / \mfk m^2\), it happens that in the continuous case \(\mfk m = \mfk m^2\), so we don’t get any smoothness data. I wonder what happens for \(C^\alpha\) manifolds for \(0 &lt; \alpha &lt; \infty\) – do you get any other information? If you know, let me know!</p> <p>Finally, the ultimate program to avoid talking about manifolds and topological spaces and just doing algebra is to think about these algebraic structures called \(C^\infty\)-rings! These are rings that are basically “closed with respect to smooth composition,” as mentioned in Nestruev’s book. This is the desired approach used to think about manifolds from the lens of <em>synthetic differential geometry</em>. Apparently Lawvere was thinking about this in the 60s, and here’s a link to the one non-nLab <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1001.0023">survey paper(?)</a> I could find on the topic. This seems really cool! It feels like people who are up on HoTT and univalent mathematics would probably really like encoding a manifold in this way, and someday if agda-unimath gets to a point to where we could think about defining a manifold, this might be the way to do it.</p> <hr/> <p></p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>which apparently has a ‘sh’ sound when referring to the book, and not when referring to the author <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2"> <p>I had a pretty traumatic moment when I learned that localizing a ring \(A\) at a prime ideal \(\mfk p\) means you invert everything <em>not</em> in the prime ideal, as opposed to localizing at an element where you just invert the element <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3"> <p>one of the coolest exercises that I did in my manifolds class taught by Prof. Reyer Sjamaar was to show that the germ of smooth functions at a point \(p \in M\), \(C^\infty_{M, p}\) was a local ring with unique maximal ideal \(\mfk m_p\). It turns out that \(\mfk m_p / \mfk m_p^2 \iso T_p^* M\), the cotangent space at \(p\), which allows you to define the tangent space via this ring. I guess this is good evidence for what I’m going to say later, but before looking into this business, this was just about the only cool thing that I knew about these rings. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:3:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4"> <p>of all places to find this kind of a fact, this would not have come to mind at all LOL <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:5"> <p>DON’T YELL AT ME <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:6"> <p>I dare not say much more about this because I don’t really know much about functional analysis, but it seems like in general doing this sort of thing to rings of continuous functions on a topological space and studying these things leads one to naturally think about C*-algebras and Banach algebras. idk, the relevant keywords seem to be “Gelfand representation” and “the Gelfand-Naimark Theorem”? I feel like I’ve encountered this last theorem before and thinking it was very cool but it’s beyond the scope of this article for now… <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:7"> <p>Jet Nestruev is actually a pen name for a fairly large group of Russian authors a la Bourbaki, except they put all of their names in the preface of the book <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="algebra"/><category term="topology"/><category term="geometry"/><category term="comm-alg"/><category term="alg-geo"/><category term="diff-top"/><category term="gen-top"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[in which we algebraify a manifold and I read lots of fanfiction]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">help what is an integer</title><link href="https://blu-bird.github.io/blog/2024/integers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="help what is an integer"/><published>2024-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blu-bird.github.io/blog/2024/integers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blu-bird.github.io/blog/2024/integers/"><![CDATA[<p>okay, I suppose I know what <em>the</em> integers are, but I didn’t know what an <em>algebraic</em> integer was until I was sitting in an algebraic number theory class for the first time. Imagine it’s the first day of class, and we see a brand-new definition that’s going to be the jumping-off point for the next fifteen weeks:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Definition (I).</strong> Let \(K\) be a finite-dimensional (field) extension of \(\QQ\). An \(\alpha \in K\) is an <em>algebraic integer</em> if it is the root of a <em>monic</em> non-zero polynomial \(f \in \ZZ[x]\).</p> </blockquote> <p>The definition itself is simple enough… but why call it an integer, and why should we think of these things as integers?</p> <h3 id="first-passes">first passes</h3> <p>Before we continue, we should at least check to see if this is a meaningful definition viewed from the lens of “being an integer.” And at first glance, I think it’s clear not all elements of a general \(K/\QQ\) are algebraic integers. For instance, the rational number \(\frac 12 \in \QQ \subseteq K\) is the root of \(2x - 1 \in \ZZ[x]\), but you can’t find any monic polynomial in \(\ZZ[x]\) that has \(\frac 12\) has a root. On the other hand, the integer \(17 \in \QQ\) is the root of a monic polynomial \(x - 17 \in \ZZ[x]\), and as expected, this definition says it should be an integer. Furthermore, things that seem pretty integer-y in other fields are roots of monic polynomials in \(\ZZ[x]\). For instance, if \(K = \QQ(i)\), \(i \in K\) seems like it should be integral, and it is – it’s the root of the monic polynomial \(x^2 + 1 \in \ZZ[x]\). In general, noting that \(\ZZ[i] \subseteq \QQ(i)\) is called the ring of Gaussian <em>integers</em>, anything of the form \(a + bi\) for \(a, b \in \ZZ\) should also be an integer under this definition. Can we find a corresponding monic polynomial that has \(a+bi\) as a root? (Maybe pause to think about it before continuing, if you can’t think of how to construct this right away.)</p> <p>It’s a little contrived, but yes! Consider \(x^2 - 2ax + a^2 + b^2 \in \ZZ[x]\), which has roots \(a \pm bi\) from the quadratic formula. So this feels like a pretty reasonable distinction to make for elements of a number field (finite-dimensional extension of \(\QQ\)) \(K\), since it seems to delineate elements of \(K\) that feel reasonably integral from other elements that aren’t. So this definition feels pretty sensible to me and we can move on.</p> <p>Mechanically, as the course progresses, I get used to working with this definition, but for some reason, the intuition behind <em>why</em> this is the right definition to describe integrality eludes me. Intuitively, I feel like the problem with this definition is that it doesn’t really mesh with any intuitive understanding of how integers work or any property that has to do with \(\ZZ\). The only real idea I have is that the integrality is surely reflected in the fact that it’s a root of a polynomial in \(\ZZ[x]\), but the monic condition doesn’t really give me any real intuition to latch onto.</p> <p>One slightly modified definition that intuitively seems like it should be clearly equivalent to this first one defines algebraic integers in terms of their minimal polynomials instead:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Definition (II).</strong> Let \(K\) be a finite-dimensional field extension of \(\QQ\). An \(\alpha \in K\) is an <em>algebraic integer</em> if the minimal polynomial \(p_\alpha\) of \(\alpha\) over \(\QQ\) is in \(\ZZ[x]\).</p> </blockquote> <p>I think it’s pretty clear that these two definitions are similar in flavor, and showing that Def. (II) implies Def. (I) is basically immediate. Going the other way requires a little bit of thought, though. First, pick any monic \(f \in \ZZ[x]\) that has \(\alpha\) as a root, and factor it into irreducibles over \(\ZZ[x]\). Each of these factors must be monic, and we can see that \(\alpha\) has to be a root of one of these factors since \(\ZZ[x]\) is an integral domain. So then suppose \(g \in \ZZ[x]\) is irreducible and has \(\alpha\) as a root. But then we know that by Gauss’ Lemma, \(g\) being monic and irreducible in \(\ZZ[x]\) implies that it’s irreducible in \(\QQ[x]\), so \(g\) is actually just the minimal polynomial \(p_\alpha\), and in fact \(g = p_\alpha \in \ZZ[x]\), as desired. It certainly makes intuitive sense that these definitions are equivalent since all we’re really doing is forcing the polynomial that \(\alpha\) is a root of to also be irreducible, and as it turns out, requiring irreducibility of the polynomial doesn’t change the definition at all.</p> <p>The course continues, and more equivalent definitions and ways of characterizing algebraic integers are introduced, but none of them sink in for me intuitively at that point either. We also talk about a lot of other cool number theory stuff – I glimpse into the world of Dedekind domains, Minkowski’s Theorem comes back when I least expect it, my mind is blown by how nicely things Galois mesh with the theory, etc. And that’s it! I end up finding algebraic number theory very cool and interesting even though I get a little lost, and I make half-baked plans to revisit it at some point in a proper course later on (and actually doing exercises, blah blah blah). But then plans change…</p> <h4 id="ghosts-of-ants-past">ghosts of ants past</h4> <p>time for a timeskip!</p> <p>It’s early August 2024, and I unexpectedly find myself at Hampshire College, playing junior staff for the annual <a href="https://hcssim.org/">Summer Studies in Mathematics</a><sup id="fnref:17"><a href="#fn:17" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> and teaching algebraic number theory to 17 very talented high school students. So far, we’ve been playing around in \(\ZZ[i]\) and \(\ZZ[\sqrt{-5}]\), investigating the unique prime factorization of elements in \(\ZZ[i]\) and its absence in \(\ZZ[\sqrt{-5}]\)<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, since \(6 = 2 \cdot 3 = (1 + \sqrt{-5})(1 - \sqrt{-5})\). However, it seems to be recoverable via unique factorization of ideals into prime ideals<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, since our students were able to come up with \(\idl 2 = \idl{2, 1+\sqrt{-5}}^2\) and \(\idl 3 = \idl{3, 1 + \sqrt{-5}} \idl{3, 1 - \sqrt{-5}}\), and similarly for \(\idl{1 + \sqrt{-5}}\) and \(\idl{1 - \sqrt{-5}}\). So, the pieces are now in place to start building theory towards figuring out how and when one can salvage unique prime factorization through ideals, and learning about the ring of integers \(\mathcal O_K\) and Dedekind domains.</p> <p>Pedagogically, learning about the ring of integers \(\mathcal O_K\) as The Example Of A Dedekind Domain feels like the right way to go. I think it’s a good idea to introduce talking about \(\mathcal O_K\) by thinking about what the “integral” elements are in various number fields<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>, and by pointing out that the initial instinct of saying “the ‘integers’ inside \(K = \QQ(\alpha)\) is just \(\ZZ[\alpha]\)” is a bad idea. Recall<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> that we can characterize any finite extension of the rationals by \(K = \QQ(\alpha)\) for some algebraic number \(\alpha\) (a root of some not-necessarily-monic polynomial in \(\ZZ[x]\)) using the Primitive Element Theorem. But, following this up with saying that the “correct analogue of the integers is \(\ZZ[\alpha]\)” <em>isn’t even a well-defined construction</em>, since the Primitive Element Theorem does not at all give a unique choice of \(\alpha\) for a given number field. As an example, consider \(\QQ(\sqrt{-3}) = \QQ(e^{\frac{2\pi i}3})\), but then this heuristic says that the “integers” inside this field should be both \(\ZZ[\sqrt{-3}]\) and \(\ZZ[e^{\frac{2\pi i}3}]\), which are distinct, non-isomorphic rings. Oops!</p> <p>To continue with this line of thinking, I need to either motivate the idea of an algebraic integer to bring in \(\mathcal O_K\) as a canonical choice of the “integral elements in a number field”, or figure out how to get at \(\mathcal O_K\) without this idea. This second option is a non-starter – finding \(\mathcal O_K\) in general is a pretty non-trivial task for a general number field. The first option is also a problem, because I don’t have a very clear mental model of an algebraic integer because I didn’t do a good enough job learning algebraic number theory my first time through. But <em>now I have no idea how to motivate the right fix to the problem of unique factorization, and I also somehow need to get my students to invent the right idea very shortly. uh oh.</em></p> <p>After a bit of Googling in a sleep-deprived haze, I stumbled across a really clever way to introduce the definition of an algebraic integer via a few carefully chosen heuristics, which I thought was both super cool and accessible enough to be put on a problem set.</p> <h4 id="clever-constraints">clever constraints</h4> <p>spoilers ahead for Hampshire 2024 students if you didn’t do this problem!<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup></p> <p>the following is inspired by <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/70088/why-do-we-use-this-definition-of-algebraic-integer?rq=1">Bill Dubuque’s answer to this math stackexchange question</a>, and is similar to <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/693541/intuition-behind-the-definition-of-algebraic-integers">Swinnerton-Dyer’s</a> introduction to the ring of algebraic integers.</p> <p>The idea goes as follows: we want to define a set \(\mathcal I\) of algebraic integers, right? We’re going to enforce a few conditions on \(\mathcal I\), and then show that these conditions basically force us to conclude that every element of \(\mathcal I\) satisfies one of the definitions of an algebraic integer that we’ve seen thus far. Here they are:</p> <ol> <li><strong>The algebraic integers \(\mathcal I\) should form a ring.</strong> After all, \(\ZZ\) is a ring, so it should be natural to assume that we should also get a whole ring of integral elements inside any finite-dimensional extension of \(\QQ\).</li> <li><strong>The only algebraic integers in \(\QQ\) are the regular integers \(\ZZ\);</strong> in other words, \(\mathcal I \cap \QQ = \ZZ\). This means that the only integral elements inside \(\QQ\) are the things we already know are integral, so this seems like a good sanity-check to have as an assumption.</li> <li><strong>If \(\alpha \in \mathcal I\), then all of its conjugates should also be in \(\mathcal I\).</strong> In other words, if \(\alpha\) and \(\alpha'\) are roots of the same minimal polynomial \(p_\alpha\) over \(\QQ\), and \(\alpha \in \mathcal I\), then \(\alpha' \in \mathcal I\). This is less of an obvious constraint, but it forces the resulting set (ring) of integral elements to be “algebraic” in the following sense. Suppose \(\mathcal I\) contained only some but not all of the conjugates of an \(\alpha \in K\). That would imply that \(\mathcal I\) would be able to distinguish between the various conjugates of a root of a minimal polynomial over \(\QQ\). In particular, the definition of \(\mathcal I\) wouldn’t be canonical anymore, since the choice of \(\mathcal I\) would have to use information about the roots themselves to decide which ones should/shouldn’t be elements of \(\mathcal I\). And in the world of algebra, making non-canonical choices is generally frowned upon<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, and so not enforcing this constraint or enforcing some negation of it would be pretty weird as a definition of a set of <em>algebraic</em> integers. Maybe you can disagree with enforcing this last condition if you like – but we will need it very shortly!</li> </ol> <p>Here’s how you arrive at Definition (II) from this. Suppose \(\alpha = \alpha_0 \in K \cap \mathcal I\) has some monic minimal polynomial \(p_\alpha = x^n + b_{n-1} x^{n-1} + \dots + b_0\) over \(\QQ\). All of the conjugates of \(\alpha\), \(\alpha_1, \dots, \alpha_{n-1}\) in \(K\) are also in \(\mathcal I\) by Condition 3. Over \(K\), \(p_\alpha\) factors as \((x - \alpha) (x - \alpha_1) \dots (x - \alpha_{n-1})\), but re-expanding, we see that</p> \[p_\alpha = x^n - \left( \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \alpha_k \right) x^{n-1} + \dots + (-1)^n \prod_{k=0}^{n-1} \alpha_k,\] <p>where the coefficients \(b_i\) of \(p_\alpha\) are all in \(\mathcal I\), since by Vieta’s formulas they’re all sums of products of some \(\alpha_k\)s, and \(\mathcal I\) is a ring by Condition 1. However, each coefficient \(b_i\) is also in \(\QQ\) since \(p_\alpha \in \QQ[x]\), so \(b_i \in \mathcal I \cap \QQ\). But then by Condition 2, \(\mathcal I \cap \QQ = \ZZ\), so \(b_i\) is an integer! In particular, the minimal polynomial of \(\alpha\) is in \(\ZZ[x]\). This means \(\alpha\) exactly satisfies Definition (II).</p> <p>However, going the other way and verifying that Conditions 1, 2, and 3 hold for the collection of algebraic integers satisfying one of our previous definitions gets a little sticky. Showing that Definition (II) satisfies Condition 3 is relatively quick. Condition 2 is also pretty clear – to see this, take an element \(\frac m n \in \QQ\) where \(\gcd(m, n) = 1\). \(\frac m n\) has a linear minimal polynomial over \(\QQ\), being \(x - \frac m n\), but it’s only possible to clear denominators and end up with a monic minimal polynomial in \(\ZZ[x]\) iff \(n = \pm 1\). However, verifying Condition 1 is harder – it’s not at all clear that \(\mathcal I\) as defined by Definitions (I) or (II) gives you a ring. In fact, when I saw Definition (II) for the first time, I was absolutely convinced that the addition and multiplication operations on the resulting ring of algebraic integers had to be induced from some strange other construction. There is in fact no shenanigans here – the ring structure literally is the good ol’ addition and multiplication of the underlying field, which is a little mind-boggling. Arguing this directly from Definitions (I) or (II) requires a good amount of work though, and personally, I don’t think the argument coming directly from these definitions is particularly enlightening. At least, it’s no more enlightening than showing that these definitions are equivalent to a secret <em>third</em> definition of an algebraic integer.</p> <p>… wait, there’s a <strong>third</strong> definition?</p> <h3 id="a-second-attempt">a second attempt</h3> <p>the program ends with a generally successful speedrun to establish the properties of a Dedekind domain for \(\mathcal O_K = \mathcal I \cap K\), ending with examples of some terrible rings<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup>, learning about prime and maximal ideals, and finally un-breaking math with the help of ideal factorization (in the right places)! Rooms are cleaned and packed, comments are written, and everyone goes home. No more algebraic number theory to be done – except for the fact that one of my students lodged the following idea in my brain, which was rattling around in there for several weeks after the program ended:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Idea:</strong> Monic polynomials are nice in \(\ZZ[x]\) because they’re the only things you can divide by in \(\ZZ[x]\) to get remainders of strictly lower degree.</p> </blockquote> <p>This idea permanently altered my brain chemistry and is the reason why the rest of the article you’re reading now exists. I felt like this had something to do with the integrality condition and said something about why algebraic integers are the right collection of numbers to study – remember from Definition (I) that roots of monic polynomials are precisely algebraic integers! After a lot of thinking, it turns out there is kind of a connection, and it’s related to another promising intuitive way to get at an algebraic integer. But first:</p> <h4 id="an-experiment">an experiment</h4> <p>i conducted an experiment on math/physics undergraduates over Discord teehee</p> <p>Inspired by my recent experiences at Hampshire, I wanted to see if one could intuitively develop Definitions (I) or (II) for an algebraic integer just by being posed the question “what makes something integral inside a number field<sup id="fnref:1:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>?”. Thankfully, someone actually interacted with my nonsense, and we ended up landing on the following question to ponder:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Question:</strong> Inside \(\QQ\), what is the difference between \(\frac 12\) (clearly not an integer) and \(2\) (clearly an integer)?</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p><strong>Answer.</strong> Having a non-trivial denominator is what separates fractions like \(\frac 12\) from integers like \(2\).</p> </blockquote> <p>This might seem silly, but in \(\QQ\), this <em>is</em> a defining difference between an integer and a rational number – rational numbers that are not integers must have denominators that are not \(\pm 1\), which we’ll call “non-trivial”. But then we’ve just replaced our question by another one:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Question:</strong> How should one test in general whether or not some \(\alpha \in K\) “doesn’t have a non-trivial denominator”?</p> </blockquote> <p>As a question, this maybe feels a little bit too open-ended for a class and gives bad “guess what the idea in my head is” vibes pedagogically. However, in this conversation, we arrived at this question after thinking about examples of several rings of integers, equipped with their corresponding norms<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup>. An analysis-minded individual might then be led to think about sequences of elements in these rings.</p> <p>A good candidate of a sequence to consider for any \(\alpha \in K\) is the sequence \(a_n = \alpha^n\) for \(n \in \ZZ^+\). As a silly example, let’s suppose we restrict to taking \(\alpha \in \QQ\) and \(\alpha\) is not an integer. Then in the resulting sequence, every element has a non-trivial denominator. In particular, the denominators we get are strictly increasing, and are all powers of some integer. For instance, in the case of \(\alpha = \frac 12\), when we take the sequence \(a_n = \frac 1 {2^n}\) for all \(n \in \ZZ^+\), the denominators of the elements of our sequence are \(2^n\), powers of \(2\). In particular, \(a_n\) is never an integer, which can be shown inductively from the fact that \(a_1 = \alpha = \frac 12\) has a non-trivial denominator. However, if \(\alpha\) has no non-trivial denominator (i.e. it’s a regular integer), \(a_n \in \ZZ\) for all \(n\). So the sequence of powers of \(\alpha\), \(a_n\), treats elements in \(\QQ\) with and without non-trivial denominators differently depending on whether the elements of \(a_n\) are integers or not. In this sense, \(a_n\) becomes an interesting sequence to study in this context.</p> <p>Let’s consider our simplest field extension \(K = \QQ(i)\), and \(\alpha \in K\). As a first easy example, even in the case where \(\alpha = i\) (which we want to be integral), \(a_n\) is no longer all integers – but \(a_2 = i^2 = -1\) is, which is something! But it’s too much to ask that \(\alpha\) be a perfect \(m\)th root of an integer, since in general, we want the “Gaussian integer” \(\alpha = x + yi\) for arbitrary \(x,y \in \ZZ\) to also be an integral element, which may not be a perfect root of an integer. What happens to \(a_n\) in this general case?</p> <p>We can start by analyzing a few values of this sequence. First, we can compute \(a_2\). Note that \(a_2 = \alpha^2 = (x+yi)^2 = x^2 - y^2 + 2xyi\) is no longer a pure integer, but it still looks pretty integral since it has real part \(x^2 - y^2\) and imaginary part \(2xy\), both of which are integers. We can kind of “correct” the imaginary part of \(a_2\) to get an actual element of \(\ZZ\) by subtracting off \(2x\) times \(a_1\) from \(a_2\). Computing,</p> \[a_2 - 2x a_1 = x^2 - y^2 + 2xyi - 2x(x + yi) = x^2 - y^2 - 2x^2 = -x^2 - y^2\] <p>which definitely is a normal integer! Let’s call \(a_2 - 2x a_1 = C \in \ZZ\). We can now use this identity recursively to show that \(a_n\) can be added to an integer multiple of \(a_1\) to form an integer for all \(n \geq 2\). For instance,</p> \[a_3 = \alpha a_2 = \alpha(2x a_1 + C) = 2x a_2 + C a_1.\] <p>But now we can write \(a_2\) in terms of \(a_1\) and integers, so now</p> \[a_3 = 2x (2x a_1 + C) + C a_1 = (4x^2 + C) a_1 + 2x C.\] <p>and therefore \(a_3 - (4x^2 + C)a_1 = 2x C\), an integer. One could similarly imagine doing this for \(a_4, a_5, \dots\). Notice that once we find a way to add an integer multiple of \(a_1\) to \(a_2 = \alpha^2\) to get an element of \(\ZZ\), we can do this for any power of \(\alpha^n\) for \(n \geq 2\) by recursion. Precisely, for \(n \geq 2\), there exists some integer multiple of \(a_1\) such that \(a_n + M_n \alpha_1 \in \ZZ\) for some \(M_n \in \ZZ\). This works in the case of \(\alpha = i\) in a silly way since \(a_2 = i^2 = -1 \in \ZZ\), but we actually need to add non-trivial multiples of \(a_1 = i\) to say, \(a_3\), to get an element of \(\ZZ\).</p> <p>Note that something similar <em>never</em> holds for \(\alpha \in \QQ\) not an integer. Revisiting the case of \(\alpha = \frac 12\), note that \(a_n + \sum_{k=1}^{n-1} M_k a_k \not \in \ZZ\) for any choice of integers \(M_k \in \ZZ\). Suppose for the sake of contradiction that \(\frac 1{2^n} + \sum_{k=1}^{n-1} \frac{M_k}{2^k} = C \in \ZZ\), but then \(1 + \sum_{k=1}^{n=1} 2^{n-k} M_k = 2^n C\). In mod \(2\) (which is exactly the denominator of \(\alpha\)), we see that this equation never holds. The same argument also holds for other rational numbers, like \(\alpha = \frac 32\). Here, the same argument goes through, with the critical step being that the numerator \(3\) is relatively prime to the denominator \(2\).</p> <p>So maybe this is a little contrived, but a possible answer to our question is:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Answer.</strong> A number \(\alpha \in K\) “doesn’t have a nontrivial denominator” iff there exists some power of \(\alpha\), \(\alpha^n\) for \(n \in \ZZ^+\), for which \(\alpha^n + \sum_{k=1}^{n-1} c_k \alpha^k \in \ZZ\) for some \(c_k\) integers. It then follows that for all \(m \geq n\), \(\alpha^m + \sum_{k=1}^{n-1} d_k \alpha^k \in \ZZ\) for some suitably-chosen \(d_k \in \ZZ\).</p> </blockquote> <p>Let’s view this in the following way from the point of view of rings. For any \(\alpha\), the sequence \(a_n = \alpha^n\) additively generates the elements of the ring \(\ZZ[\alpha]\), by definition. When \(\alpha\) feels integral, like in the case when \(\alpha = x + yi \in K = \QQ(i)\) for \(x,y\) integers, since we showed that \(\alpha^2 + 2x \alpha \in \ZZ\) and therefore for all \(n \geq 2\), \(\alpha^n + M_n \alpha = C_n \in \ZZ\) for some \(M_n \in \ZZ\), we see that all of the elements of \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) can be written in terms of integer linear combinations of \(\alpha\) and \(1\). On the other hand, when \(\alpha\) doesn’t feel integral, like when \(\alpha = \frac 12\) or \(\frac 32\), the rings \(\ZZ[\frac 12]\) and \(\ZZ[\frac 32]\) feel “big” in a certain sense. (Note: \(\ZZ[\frac 32]\) is actually the exact same ring as \(\ZZ[\frac 12]\) since \(\frac 32 = 1 + \frac 12\), and so any expression with \(\frac 32\)s in it can be rewritten in terms of \(\frac 12\)s and other integers, and vice versa.) Since we can never write \(\frac 1{2^n}\) as an integer linear combination of smaller powers of \(\frac 12\), we might have to use an arbitrarily large power of \(\frac 12\) to write down an arbitrary element in \(\ZZ[\frac 12]\) as an integer linear combination of other ones. This is reflected by the idea that we get some redundancy from relations like \(i^2 = - 1\) in \(\ZZ[i]\) or \((x+yi)^n = -M_n (x+yi) + C_n\) in \(\ZZ[x+yi]\), but no such relation holds in \(\ZZ[\frac 12]\). This is the exact property we want that somehow makes \(i\) and \(x+yi\) integers but \(\frac 12\) and \(\frac 32\) <em>not</em> integers, and will give us our third definition!</p> <h4 id="interlude-generators-and-modules">interlude: generators and modules</h4> <p>but first, we have to talk about generators. If you already know the language of modules over a ring, definitely go ahead and skip to the next section. Also, if you’re familiar with generators of a group, you should mostly be fine. The exposition that follows is the minimum amount of content needed to understand what follows, and is especially targeted towards Hampshire students, so some statements might not be phrased in their full generality, oops.</p> <details><summary>expand me for some exposition about generators and modules</summary> <p>One might see generators in the context of groups first:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Def.</strong> A group \(G\) is <em>generated</em> by a set \(S\) (denoted \(G = \idl S\)) if every element \(g \in G\) is a product of elements \(s_1 s_2 \dots s_n\) where \(s_i \in S\) for all \(1 \leq i \leq n\). \(G\) is <em>finitely-generated</em> if there exists a finite set \(S\) that generates \(G\).</p> </blockquote> <p>Now, we are talking about rings here, but rings are abelian groups under addition. As such, it makes sense to talk about rings as being “finitely-generated” as an abelian group, and actually this would be enough for our purposes. You can stop reading now if you want. However, people often state this property differently and tend not to reference groups at all, instead opting to say this in the context of a more abstract setting. In particular, people tend to talk about this property by using more linear algebra-style intuition. Recall:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Def.</strong> A field \(K / \QQ\) is spanned by a set \(S \subseteq K\) if every element in \(K\) is a rational linear combination of elements in \(S\), i.e. for all \(k \in K\), \(k = \sum_{s \in S} q_s \cdot s\) where all of the \(q_s \in \QQ\). \(K\) is <em>finite-dimensional</em> if \(S\) can be chosen to be a finite set.</p> </blockquote> <p>From here, people generalize to not just allow \(K\) to be any field extension of \(\QQ\), but allow \(K\) to be an arbitrary abelian group under addition that also has a multiplication by elements in \(\QQ\). This yields what people call a <em>vector space</em> over \(\QQ\). You can even generalize one step further and allow the multiplication on \(K\) to be by elements in any ring \(R\), and you get:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Def.</strong> A <em>module</em> over a (commutative) ring \(R\) (with unit \(\Bbb 1\)) is an abelian group \((M, +)\) with a scalar multiplication by elements of \(R\) that is associative, has an identity \(\Bbb 1\), and distributes over addition. \(M\) is also called an <em>\(R\)-module</em>.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p><strong>Def.</strong> An \(R\)-module \(M\) is <em>generated</em> by a set \(S \subseteq M\) if every element in \(M\) can be written as an \(R\)-linear combination of elements in \(S\), i.e. for all \(m \in M\), \(m = \sum_{s \in S} r_s \cdot s\) where all of the \(r_s \in R\). \(M\) is <em>finitely-generated</em> if \(S\) can be chosen to be finite.</p> </blockquote> <p>We don’t really need think about \(R\)-modules for a general ring \(R\) – what we really care about is whether elements of \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) can be expressed as \(\ZZ\)-linear combinations of a finite set of elements in \(\ZZ[\alpha]\), so we really only need to view \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) as a \(\ZZ\)-module. But it turns out \(\ZZ\)-modules are just a fancy word for abelian groups! Any abelian group \((G, +)\) can be thought of as a \(\ZZ\)-module in the following way – given an arbitrary element \(g \in G\) and \(n \in \ZZ^+\), define \(n \cdot g = \sum_{i=1}^n g = g + g + \dots + g\), in the same way that multiplying a number by 17 means adding up 17 copies of that number. By extension, we should define \(0 \cdot g = e\), where \(e\) is the identity in \(G\), since we’re adding zero things together. Extrapolating further, \((-n) \cdot g = \sum_{i=1}^n g^{-1}\), since \(g^{-1}\) can be thought of as “\(-g\)” in an abelian group if the (additive) identity is “\(0\)”, and \((-n) \cdot g\) is kinda like \(n \cdot (-g)\) (which should really be \(n \cdot g^{-1}\)). This gives you a scalar multiplication by \(\ZZ\) on \(G\) that automatically turns it into a \(\ZZ\)-module. (And definitionally, any \(\ZZ\)-module is an abelian group, so these notions are equivalent.)</p> <p>Moreover, it’s not too hard to check for yourself that the concept of being finitely-generated in terms of \(\ZZ\)-modules is the exact same thing as being finitely-generated as an abelian group! So, we don’t <em>really</em> need to bring in the abstract language of modules when we can get away with thinking about abelian groups, and if you’re more comfortable with that, you can kind of ignore the above.</p> <p>As an aside, though, modules <em>are</em> the language that is most commonly used when describing linear combinations with coefficients in an arbitrary ring, and they describe a much more general class of algebraic structures. Just to briefly justify why people like modules, modules are to the vector spaces of linear algebra as rings are to fields. Recall that rings can be pretty wild and wacky and have a lot of general theory, whereas fields are more constrained in the kinds of behaviors they can exhibit. In the same way, modules encode a really broad class of algebraic structures, whereas vector spaces are relatively constrained in their structure. Modules therefore are more flexible in the kinds of objects that they can represent. Personally, I was initially skeptical about why one should ever think about modules when I first saw them, but as I’ve gotten more used to thinking about them, the more I think they have a good amount of complexity to be fun and interesting to play with while also being useful.</p> </details> <p>…</p> <p>Enough digression for now – let’s get to</p> <h4 id="the-secret-third-thing">the secret third thing</h4> <p>for a given \(\alpha \in K\) with \(K\) finite-dimensional over \(\QQ\), to think about the integrality of \(\alpha\), we’re thinking about how “big” \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) is as a \(\ZZ\)-module/abelian group. In our previous examples with \(\alpha = \frac 12\) versus \(\alpha = i\), note that \(\ZZ[i]\) is finitely-generated with generating set \(\set{1, i}\). However, note that \(\ZZ[\frac 12]\) is weird because it’s not finitely generated! A generating set for \(\ZZ[\frac 12]\) is \(\set{\frac 1 {2^n} : n \in \NN}\), but can there be any finite generating set? Turns out, no – if we did, we would have an upper bound on the largest possible denominator of a fraction we could achieve with \(\ZZ\)-linear combinations, and we know that \(\ZZ[\frac 12]\) has fractions with arbitrarily large denominators.</p> <p>This leads us to a new definition for integrality from this point of view:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Definition (III).</strong> Let \(K\) be a finite-dimensional field extension of \(\QQ\). An \(\alpha \in K\) is an <em>algebraic integer</em> if \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) is a finitely-generated \(\ZZ\)-module (abelian group, under addition).</p> </blockquote> <p>This is pretty different from Definitions (I) and (II)! I like this definition intuitively because the integrality is suggested by the fact that \(\alpha\) now has to “play nicely” in some sense with \(\ZZ\). On the other hand, this definition feels like a more abstract condition, whereas Definitions (I) and (II) feel more concrete since they deal with polynomials. Speaking of which, does Definition (III) really describe the same collection of numbers as Definitions (I) and (II)?</p> <p>Suppose you were to take Definition (I) or Definition (II) as your definition of an algebraic integer. Recall<sup id="fnref:4:1"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> that by the First Isomorphism Theorem that \(\ZZ[\alpha] \cong \ZZ[x] / \idl{p_\alpha}\), where \(p_\alpha\) is the minimal polynomial of \(\alpha\) over \(\ZZ\) with degree \(n\). Assuming Definition (II) of an algebraic integer, \(p_\alpha\) has to be monic! Now we can use the Idea from above – when dividing any polynoimal \(f \in \ZZ[x]\) by \(p_\alpha\), we can write \(f = q p_\alpha + r\) for \(q, r \in \QQ[x]\) where \(\deg r &lt; n\) because \(p_\alpha\) is monic! Actually, because \(p_\alpha\) is monic, we can also force \(q, r \in \ZZ[x]\) if we think a little harder. Now, if we consider the ring homomorphism from \(\ZZ[x] \to \ZZ[\alpha]\) that evaluates any polynomial \(f\) at \(\alpha\), we see that \(f\) gets sent to \(f(\alpha) = q(\alpha) p_\alpha(\alpha) + r(\alpha) = q(\alpha) \cdot 0 + r(\alpha) = r(\alpha)\), and since this homomorphism is surjective, we see that \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) consists of polynomials in \(\alpha\) that have degree less than \(n\)! Therefore, the set \(\set{1, \alpha, \dots, \alpha^{n - 1}}\) is a generating set for \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) and so \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) is finitely generated, as required by Definition (III). A similar vibes-based way to see this is that \(p_\alpha\) gives an expression for \(\alpha^n\) as an integer linear combination of all of the lower powers of \(\alpha\), so using this one can express all powers of \(\alpha\) in terms of integer linear combinations of \(\set{1, \alpha, \dots, \alpha^{n-1}}\). So Definition (I)/Definition (II) certainly imply Definition (III)!</p> <p>Let’s try this on our non-example for \(\alpha = \frac 12\) – here, \(p_\alpha = 2x - 1\). We actually saw this on a problem set at Hampshire – when you consider \(\ZZ[x] / \idl{2x - 1}\), you actually can’t use the quotiented ideal to cancel out powers of \(x\) with odd coefficients, so \(\set{1, x, x^2, \dots}\) are all nonzero elements in this ring and the higher powers of \(x\) can’t be written in terms of the lower ones with integer coefficients! This is exactly like how \(\set{1, \frac 12, \frac 14, \dots}\) are all nonzero elements in \(\ZZ[\frac 12]\), and you can’t write \(\frac 1{2^n}\) as an integral linear combination of \(\set{1, \frac 12, \dots, \frac 1{2^{n-1}}}\), which is kind of what we expect under the isomorphism \(\ZZ[x] / \idl{2x - 1} \cong \ZZ[\frac 12]\) given by substituting \(x\) for \(\frac 12\). In general, any element with a non-monic minimal polynomial over \(\ZZ\) won’t admit a general way to write a power of \(\alpha\) as an integer combination of its lower powers, which is a good heuristic for seeing that \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) is infinitely generated.</p> <p>But how do we actually show Definition (III) implies Definition (I)/(II)? Ah… this is a little trickier and requires a little bit of matrix magic. Let’s consider as an example \(\alpha = 1 + 4i\), and so \(\ZZ[\alpha] = \ZZ[1+4i] = \ZZ[4i]\), since the \(1\) already is an integer. Note that this ring has generating set \(\set{1, 4i}\). Now here comes a bit of a trick: we’re going to multiply \(\alpha\) by each of the generators of \(\ZZ[4i]\), and write the result in terms of integer multiples of the generators (which must be possible, since they were generators, after all):</p> \[\alpha \cdot 1 = 1 + 4i = 1 \cdot 1 + 1 \cdot 4i \qquad \alpha \cdot 4i = -16 + 4i = -16 \cdot 1 + 1 \cdot 4i\] <p>Let’s rewrite these equations like so:</p> \[(\alpha - 1) \cdot 1 + (-1) \cdot 4i = 0 \qquad 16 \cdot 1 + (\alpha - 1) \cdot 4i = 0\] <p>I’m writing these equations in a weird way, because I want to rewrite these equations in matrix form in the following way:</p> \[\bmat{\alpha - 1 &amp; -1 \\ 16 &amp; \alpha - 1} \bmat{1 \\ 4i} = \bmat{0 \\ 0}\] <p>Now, I claim that the matrix \(A = \tbmat{\alpha - 1 &amp; -1 \\ 16 &amp; \alpha - 1}\) is not invertible. If it had some inverse \(B\), then I could multiply by \(B\) on both sides to get \(\bmat{1 \\ 4i} = B \bmat{0 \\ 0} = \bmat{0 \\ 0}\), which is a contradiction. Therefore, \(A\) is not invertible, so its determinant must be zero. This implies that \((\alpha - 1)^2 + 16 = 0\), which magically yields a polynomial with integer coefficients that has \(\alpha\) has a root. This polynomial expands to be \(\alpha^2 - 2\alpha + 17\), which is also monic! In the specific case of \(\alpha = 1 + 4i\), then, we can do this kind of linear algebra magic to cook up a monic polynomial that has \(\alpha\) as a root.</p> <p>This argument indicates how one can show that Definition (III) implies Definition (I). I’m going to hide it in case you don’t want to see the general argument:</p> <details><summary>expand me if you do want to see how to do this in general</summary> <p>First, we know that by Definition (III) that \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) is finitely generated, perhaps with generating set \(\set{b_1, \dots, b_k}\) for some \(k \in \NN\). In particular, for every \(1 \leq i \leq k\), \(\alpha b_i\) is some integer combination \(\sum_{j=1}^k a_{ij} b_j\) for some \(a_{ij} \in \ZZ\). If we form the coefficients \(a_{ij}\) into a matrix \(A\) such that the \((i, j)\)th entry of \(A\) is \(a_{ij}\), and letting \(\mathbf b = \tbmat{b_1 \\ \vdots \\ b_k}\), this system of equations can be thought of as the matrix equation \(\alpha I_k \cdot \mathbf b = A \mathbf b\). Doing some rearranging, we can say that \((\alpha I_k - A) \cdot \mathbf b = 0\), so by the same logic as above, \(\alpha I_k - A\) is not invertible and has determinant zero. Note that \(f(x) = \det(x I_k - A)\) is a monic polynomial in \(x\) with root \(\alpha\), so \(f\) is the desired polynomial we want for Definition (I). This is a little messy, but it works!</p> </details> <p>… but now we’ve shown these definitions are equivalent! Nice!</p> <p>The neat thing about Definition (III) is that it really quickly allows you to see that algebraic integers are a ring. Let’s knock this out. Suppose \(\alpha\) and \(\beta\) are algebraic integers. Then, by Definition (III) we know that \(\ZZ[\alpha]\) and \(\ZZ[\beta]\) are finitely generated, perhaps with generators \(\set{a_1, \dots, a_k}\) and \(\set{b_1, \dots, b_l}\), respectively. Now, we claim that \(\ZZ[\alpha, \beta]\) is generated by \(\set{a_i b_j : 1 \leq i \leq k, 1 \leq j \leq l}\), where \(\ZZ[\alpha, \beta]\) is obtained by adding all the powers of \(\alpha\) and \(\beta\) and their pairwise products to \(\ZZ\). Note that for any non-negative integers \(e, f\), \(\alpha^e = \sum_{i=1}^k c_i a_i\) and \(\beta^f = \sum_{j=1}^l d_j b_j\) for some integer coefficients \(c_i, d_j\). Then, \(\alpha^e \beta^f = \sum_{i=1}^k \sum_{j=1}^l c_i d_j a_i b_j\), so all products of powers of \(\alpha\) and \(\beta\) are generated by integer linear combinations of this finite generating set of \(kl\) elements. Moreover, \(\ZZ[\alpha + \beta]\) and \(\ZZ[\alpha \beta]\) are both subrings of \(\ZZ[\alpha, \beta]\), so these rings must also be finitely generated \(\ZZ\)-modules (abelian groups). But then \(\alpha + \beta\) and \(\alpha \beta\) are algebraic integers by Definition (III), so the algebraic integers must form a ring!</p> <p>I hope the relative slickness of this argument at least shows that Definition (III) has a lot of utility as another definition for an algebraic integer, and that the preceding exposition makes it feel more intuitive while also meshing well with the idea of being a root of a monic polynomial that pervades Definitions (I) and (II). Not to say that the first two definitions aren’t intuitive, but to believe them intuitively I feel like requires a few convictions about what an integer should be that are reasonable but might not be what you first come up with. Both definitions have their uses and different definitions are nicer for exhibiting different facts about the ring of algebraic integers \(\mathcal I\) (or \(\mathcal O_K\)). However, the fact that they’re equivalent through some manipulations is really neat and unexpected, in my opinion.</p> <p>and that’s it! I think I get what an integer is now!</p> <h3 id="coda-hitting-the-books">coda: hitting the books</h3> <p>in researching and thinking about this topic, I wanted to see how people came up with this idea in the first place. I went down a bit of a rabbit hole looking for the places where people first came up with this idea, and it turns out that a lot of this stuff came from some guys in the 19th century named Ernst Kummer and Richard Dedekind.</p> <p>Kummer came first in time, studying higher reciprocity laws. One might remember from an elementary number theory class (or program) that Carl Gauss had tons of arguments for quadratic reciprocity, which tells one how to relate the existence of solutions to \(x^2 \equiv p \mod q\) to \(x^2 \equiv q \mod p\) for primes \(p\) and \(q\). The natural generalization is to then think about whether the equations \(x^m \equiv p \mod q\) and \(x^m \equiv q \mod p\) have related sets of solutions for any \(m &gt; 2\). Several people (Gauss, Jacobi, Eisenstein) had tackled the case of \(m = 3\) and \(m = 4\) before Kummer by examining the rings \(\ZZ[i]\) and \(\ZZ[e^{\frac{2\pi i}3}]\), and Kummer was looking to build on this work and find higher reciprocity laws for any \(m\). Kummer was kind of successful in this project, but really needed to use \(\ZZ[\omega]\) for \(\omega = e^{\frac{2\pi i}m}\) to do this and assuming that \(\ZZ[\omega]\) had unique factorization. Unfortunately, as one might suspect, this isn’t true for arbitrary \(m\) – and I’ll probably revisit this in another post because we’ll probably talk about this in my abstract algebra class next quarter LOL. In any case, Kummer came up with the idea of “ideal numbers” to handle the loss of unique factorization, which is the direct historical predecessor to the modern idea of an ideal, now formalized by Dedekind.</p> <p>In formalizing and extending Kummer’s work, Dedekind is generally credited with developing the modern concept of a ring, a theory of ideals (and prime ideals), and trying to extend Kummer’s ideas to the right kinds of rings. Dedekind thought the right setting for Kummer’s ideas was the “domain of integers of algebraic number fields,” which is what we would today call the ring of integers \(\mathcal O_K\) of a finite-dimensional extension \(K / \QQ\). But how did Dedekind come up with the right definition of \(\mathcal O_K\)? The following passage (along with much of the above) comes from Israel Kleiner’s book <em>A History of Abstract Algebra</em>:</p> <blockquote> <p>But Dedekind did not motivate his definition of the domain of integers of an algebraic number field, as historian of mathematics Edwards laments: “Insofar as this is the crucial idea of the theory, the genesis of the theory appears, therefore, to be lost.”</p> </blockquote> <p>… dang. thanks Dedekind.</p> <p>I guess it’s good that we developed our own intuition for why integers are integers!</p> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:17"> <p>and if you’re interested in teaching at a very cool summer program for very talented high school students you should apply! <a href="#fnref:17" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2"> <p>ask any Hampshire 2024 student about the great town of <a href="https://www.logan.qld.gov.au/jimboomba">Jimboomba, Australia</a> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3"> <p>if you’re a Hampshire 2024 student from ANT maxi, this is what we called “stubborns” and “plabborns” <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:1"> <p>a number field \(K\) is just any finite-dimensional extension of \(\QQ\), I just don’t want to have to keep saying “finite-dimensional extension of \(\QQ\)” over and over <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:1:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4"> <p>if you’re a Hampshire student, recall that “recall” also means “learn quickly” if you’ve forgotten teehee <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:4:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p> </li> <li id="fn:5"> <p>in ANT maxi, this was the last problem on Problem Set 10, <em>Moral Resolve</em> <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:6"> <p>POV algebraists when you choose a basis when working with a vector space 😱 <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:7"> <p>like \(\ZZ[\sqrt{-3}]\) or \(\ZZ[2^{1/2^n} \mid n \in \ZZ^+]\). The first of these doesn’t have “Krull dimension 1,” i.e. it has prime ideals that are not maximal, and the second is not Noetherian, so factoring (at the ideal level or otherwise) can sometimes not terminate <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:8"> <p>You can look up how the norm \(N_{K / \QQ}\) is defined for any number field. In the case where \(K = Q(\frac 12) = \QQ\) I think you get back the regular absolute value on \(\QQ\) that you’re used to. In general though, this norm can be pretty weird depending on what \(\alpha\) specifically is, oops <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="algebra"/><category term="comm-alg"/><category term="alg-nt"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[in which I conduct an experiment and there is much ANT]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">first!</title><link href="https://blu-bird.github.io/blog/2024/first-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="first!"/><published>2024-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blu-bird.github.io/blog/2024/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blu-bird.github.io/blog/2024/first-post/"><![CDATA[<p>starting a math blog associated to this website!</p> <h2 id="wait-why-are-you-doing-this">wait why are you doing this</h2> <p>Two main reasons:</p> <ul> <li>I have an on/off relationship with structured writing and I’ve wanted to start keeping a blog again for some time</li> <li>I really enjoy reading various blogs about things I like (math included) and I hope I can make my own!</li> </ul> <p>Other than the fact that it’s fun, though, I think there are good practical reasons for maintaining a personal math blog:</p> <h4 id="sharing-math-regularly">Sharing math regularly</h4> <p>Most math I’ve written up for a class, if not notes, usually justs consists of problem set writeups. Problem set writeups are nice to be good at but are not really an ideal medium/mode for communicating mathematical ideas. Maybe yours are better than mine, but mine are often unpolished and do just enough work to convince someone with experience that I know what I’m doing. They’re not really meant for full, detailed explanations, nor are they written in a nice pedagogical way.</p> <p>Also, I think the reason I was drawn to doing talks at my undergraduate math club is because I often prepare for them by doing a lot of expository mathematical writing for the flow/topic I chose. I really like doing this because it forces me to disassemble and reassemble my knowledge into a thread that is digestible by a live audience. It also forces me to develop intuition for a given idea instead of just relying on rigorous definitions for it, which is good in general but difficult to communicate quickly, as I’ve found.</p> <p>Speaking of which:</p> <h4 id="drafts-for-things">Drafts for things</h4> <p>As mentioned, since I often do expository writing in advance of a talk I’m preparing to give, it should go the other way around as well - writing a bunch of expository mathematics should be useful for giving expository talks! I don’t think I expect to give any in the near future, but it’s nice to build a bank of potential talks over time. Also, If I happen to write about something related to research I happen to work on, this will also help with being able to write an introduction/background section for the corresponding paper quickly, or help with preparing the corresponding section for a research talk.</p> <p>However, I don’t think I want to put pressure on myself to make these blog posts the most polished things in the world. I’m not going to go out of my way to not spread misinformation on the internet, but I will make a good-faith effort to try and be as correct as possible while also being concise. Notably, in blogs that I enjoy reading, I really appreciate detailed writing that avoids being dense, and I’d like to practice this in my own writing.</p> <h4 id="space-for-ideasdetails">Space for ideas/details</h4> <p>In math classes, one of the many clichés is to leave details as an “exercise for the reader.” Sometimes I appreciate this if it’s in a topic that I don’t have a ton of investment in, but sometimes I really do want to understand some of the gory details of why something works! Some of my planned ideas for things to write about involve doing deep-dives into specific fun but complicated pieces of math, and I hope this gives me an excuse to learn about them (and also a space to complain about bringing on my own suffering).</p> <p>I’d also like to provide novel takes on topics/ideas that may not be part of the most prominent lines of thought. I think it’s nice to have alternate perspectives available on a subject, and I hope this can contribute to providing some of those perspectives for other people.</p> <h2 id="goal-setting">goal-setting</h2> <p>As a graduate student, keeping a personal blog is <em>obviously</em> the most important thing I should be doing with my time. Here are the (hopefully realistic) goals I’m setting for myself so that I don’t go/feel the need to go too overboard and to make this sustainable:</p> <ul> <li>Every quarter, produce at least 5-17 minutes worth of expository mathematical writing for the blog. Perhaps adjust over time, but no specific length requirement per post as long as it feels substantive.</li> <li>Every academic year, produce enough content that can be assembled into a typical-length talk (34 to 51 minutes, perhaps).</li> </ul> <p>Hopefully this is the beginning of a healthy, sustainable writing hobby!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[in which the blog is introduced for the first time and goals are set]]></summary></entry></feed>